<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Godlye sermon preached before the Queens Most Excellent Maiestie vpon the 17, 18, 19 verses of the 16 chapter of S. Mathew vvherein is contained the conclusion of a dialogue betweene Christ and his disciples, shewing breefely that the authoritie which the Pope of Rome doth challenge to himselfe is vnlawfully vsurped : very necessarie for these perilous times wherein the simple may perceiue their intollerable impietie, vsurping that office and action which euer appertayned vnto Christ only : published at the request of sundry godly and well disposed persons.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1585</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 125 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11924</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22237</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2330</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23276656</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23276656</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26495</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11924)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26495)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1803:32)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Godlye sermon preached before the Queens Most Excellent Maiestie vpon the 17, 18, 19 verses of the 16 chapter of S. Mathew vvherein is contained the conclusion of a dialogue betweene Christ and his disciples, shewing breefely that the authoritie which the Pope of Rome doth challenge to himselfe is vnlawfully vsurped : very necessarie for these perilous times wherein the simple may perceiue their intollerable impietie, vsurping that office and action which euer appertayned vnto Christ only : published at the request of sundry godly and well disposed persons.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 93 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Iohn Windet for Iohn Perin, and are to be sold at his shop in Paules church-yard, at the sign of the Angel,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1585]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of imprint suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew XVI, 17-19 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Popes --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26495:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26495:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26495:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26495:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A GODLYE SERMON: Preached before the Queens moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Maieſtie, vpon the 17. 18. 19. <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the</hi> 16. <hi>Chapter of S. Mathew:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVherein is contained the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of a Dialogue betweene Chriſt <hi>and his Diſciples: Shewing breefely that the</hi> authoritie which the Pope of Rome doth challenge to himſelfe, is vnlawfully vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped.</p>
            <p>Very neceſſarie for theſe perilous times <hi>wherein the ſimple may perceiue their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable impietie, vſurping that office and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which euer appertayned vnto Chriſt only.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed at the request of ſundry godly and well diſpoſed perſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ <hi>Imprinted at London by</hi> Iohn Windet for Iohn Perin, and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Paules church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, at the ſign of the <hi>Angel</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:26495:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:26495:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A godly Sermon prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched before the Queenes moſt excellent Maieſtie, vpon the 17. 18. 19. verſes of the 16. Chapter of S. Matthewe.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Matth. Chap. 16. verſ. 17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>17</hi>
                     </bibl> And Ieſus anſwered, and ſaid to him: Bleſſed art thou Simon the ſonne of Ionas: for fleſh and bloud hath not reueiled it vnto thee, but my Father which is in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>18</hi>
                     </bibl> And I ſay alſo vnto thee, that thou art Peter, and vpon this rocke I will build my Church: and the gates of hell ſhall not euercome it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>19</hi>
                     </bibl> And I will giue vnto thee the keyes of the kingdome of heauen, and whatſoeuer thou ſhalt binde vpon earth, ſhalbe bound in heauen: and whatſoeuer thou ſhalt looſe on earth, ſhalbe looſed in heauen.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words which I haue read (right honourable, &amp; beloued in our Sauioure Chriſt) containe the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of a Dialogue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene Chriſt and his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples. For we read immediatly before in the thirtéenth verſe of this ſixtéenth Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that when Ieſus came into the coaſts of <hi>Caeſarea Philippi:</hi> our Sauiour Chriſt,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:26495:4"/> partly to make tryall of the faith, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and profiting of his diſciples: ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing bene now ſo long taught by him, and ſéene ſo great &amp; wonderfull miracles: and partly to learn whether they conceiued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny better of him than the common multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude: as alſo to cauſe them to make a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of their faith and beliefe in him, in which he might ſtrengthen and confirme them againſt al troubles and perſecutions that were after to enſue: he demaunded of them all, this queſtion, whome do men ſay that I the ſonne of man am. Anſwere was made by them, that ſome ſaid he was <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 14.2.</note> for ſo ſurmiſed the <hi>Herodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> as apeareth in the <hi>14.</hi> of this Goſpel. Where it is ſayde, that when <hi>Herod</hi> the Tetrarch, who had beheaded <hi>Iohn Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt,</hi> heard of the fame of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> he ſaid vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his ſeruaunts, this is <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> that is riſen againe from the dead, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore great workes are wrought by him. Some ſaid he was <hi>Elias,</hi> being deceiued partly by the Prophecie of <hi>Malachie,</hi> miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnderſtoode, who had prophcied that <hi>Eliah</hi> the Prophet ſhould be ſent before the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the great and fearfull day of the<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Malach.</hi> 4.5.</note>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:26495:4"/> Lord, partly, by the like ſpirite they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued in Chriſt that was in <hi>Elias,</hi> as the frée libertie of rebuking vices in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcribes and Phariſées, the power of working mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, raiſing vp the dead to life againe, as <hi>Elias</hi> did. Some other thought him to be <hi>Hieremias</hi> becauſe he bare a figure of Chriſt, and for that it was ſaide of him, <hi>Beholde this day haue I ſet thee ouer the nations, and ouer the kingdomes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ierem.</hi> 1.9.</note> 
               <hi>to plucke vp, and to roote out, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroye and throw downe, to build and to plant:</hi> which was in verie déede, truely to be perfourmed in Chriſt. And they that thought him none of theſe, yet becauſe of his doctrine (for he taught them as hauing authoritie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.29.</note> not as the Scribes) and for his life and miracles they accounted him as one of the Prophets. Chriſt hearing this, to drawe out a more certaine and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of his diſciples than this was, he further demaunded of them all, but <hi>whome ſay ye that I am:</hi> as though he ſhould haue ſaid, whatſoeuer other men do thinke of mée, or howſoeuer they be diſtract in opinions, you who ought to haue better knewledge of mée, whome do
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:26495:5"/> ye thinke me to be. Then aunſwered <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Peter</hi> in the name of al the reſt: <hi>thou art Chriſt the ſonne of the liuing God.</hi> Chriſt reioycing at this true perfect and conſtant confeſſion that <hi>Peter</hi> had made, as it were in recompence and commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion therof, he burſt out into theſe words: <hi>Bleſſed art thou Simon the ſonne of Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas, for fleſh and bloud hath not reuei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it vnto thee, but my father which is in heauen, &amp;c.</hi> Which wordes are euen the concluſion of that Dialogue betwéene Chriſt and his diſciples, and do containe the approbation and commendation of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> confeſſion. In the which many things do offer them ſelues to our conſiderations, but for this preſent time and occaſion, in theſe thrée verſes, thrée eſpeciall pointes may be here obſerued by vs. The firſt from whence <hi>Peter</hi> had this knowledge &amp; faith of Chriſt, that he was the ſonne of the liuing God. Secondarily, what is the foundation and rocke, whereupon the Church of God was built. Thirdly, what the power, authoritie, &amp; commiſſion was, that is giuen vnto <hi>Peter</hi> in this place. The firſt point is declared in the firſt verſe of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:26495:5"/> this text by two meanes, firſt by remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and denying thoſe things, which might ſéeme to be the cauſe &amp; yet are not, as fleſh and bloud. Secondarily, by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing the true and perfect cauſe, which was the reuelation of Almightie GOD. For the firſt, by fleſh and bloud is meant here, the nature of man, and all his giftes that he hath naturally, as his wit, vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and wil: for ſo it is taken in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie other places of the holie Scriptures, as in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt of <hi>Saint Iohns</hi> Goſpell,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 1.12.</note> where he ſaith that ſuch as receiued Chriſt, they were borne not of bloud nor of the will of fleſh, nor of the will of man, but of God. And in the firſt to the <hi>Galathians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Galath.</hi> 1.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> where he teſtifieth, that when it pleaſed God to reueale his ſonne in him, that he ſhoulde preach him among the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated not with fleſh and bloud, and in like manner, in the ſixth to the <hi>Epheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.12.</note> exhorting vs to put on all the armour of God, that we might be able to ſtande a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the aſſaultes of the diuell, becauſe we wreſtle not againſt fleſh &amp; bloud, but againſt principalities, and powers, &amp;c. In which places as in diuerſe others alſo, by
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:26495:6"/> fleſh and bloud is meant nothing but the nature of man, and whatſoeuer is in him by his naturall birth and procreation, ſo that this phraſe and manner of ſpéech vſed of our Sauiour Chriſt here in this place doth ſignifie and declare vnto vs, that this knowledge of Chriſt, &amp; confeſſion of faith, which <hi>Peter</hi> made, he had it not of himſelf, neither by any meanes of man, but from aboue, by the manifeſtation and reuelatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God, who had opened this great myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and giuen him this faith. This doctrin ouerthroweth the iudgement and opinion of the Heathen Philoſophers, <hi>Pelagian</hi> he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes, and of the church of <hi>Rome,</hi> who wholly or in parte aſcribe the cauſe of all knowledge of God, of our faith, of the good workes we do, either to the light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, force of reaſon, or frée will and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie of man, contrarie not onely to this teſtimonie of Chriſt here in this place, which depriueth man of all knowledge of Chriſt, but alſo vnto the whole tenour of the Scripture in other places, where both generally and in particular ſorte, is taken away al vnderſtanding and perceuerance, in matters appertaing vnto faith, religion,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:26495:6"/> and the true knowledge of God. Firſt, for proofe hereof, that it is generally denyed vnto man of himſelfe, or by the reache of his own wit and vnderſtanding to attaine to the knowledge of Chriſt, &amp; thoſe things which appertaine to the kingdome of God, what can be more plaine then that <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifieth to the contrarie in the firſt of the <hi>Corinthes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.</note> and the ſecond Chapter, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The naturall man is not able to perceiue the things of the ſpirite of God. The naturall man, that is the man that hath no farther knowledge then he hath by the light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, whoſe knowledge, and iudgement is not lightened and cleared by the ſpirite of God (for ſo is this terme expounded by <hi>Iude</hi> in his Epiſtle, in the <hi>19.</hi> verſe<note place="margin">Iude. <hi>19.</hi> v.</note>) that that man perceiueth not theſe thinges which appertaine vnto the ſpirit of God, For proofe hereof he adioyneth two rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, the one is becauſe ſpirituall thinges are fooliſhneſſe vnto him: the other, that he cannot knowe thoſe things, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned, that is they cannot be known but of them that are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dewed with the ſpirite of God. For as
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:26495:7"/> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifieth,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11.</note> as no man knoweth the thinges of man, ſaue the Spirite of a man which is within him: euen ſo the things of God knoweth no man, but the ſpirite of God, and therefore in the ſame Chapter he ſheweth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 9.</note> that thoſe thinges which God hath prepared for them that loue him, are ſuch as eye hath not ſéene, eare hath not heard, neither yet hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the minde of man, ſo that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the outward ſenſes, nor yet by the vnderſtanding of man, we are able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the things of God, but it is the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of God which openeth them vnto vs, which ſearcheth all things, yea the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of Gods ſecretes.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10.</note> In reſpect of this great ignorance in vs, and want of power and abilitie to perceiue, the myſteries of Gods kingdome and of our ſaluation, the holie Ghoſt hath by moſt notable termes and Epithetes, whereby he deſcribeth the nature of man, declared vnto vs, how vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly we be voide of all knowledge and iudgement in ſpirituall matters. What can more effectually, and ſignificantly, ſhewe foorth that vnto vs, then for vs to be termed darkeneſſe it ſelfe, which is don
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:26495:7"/> not in a fewe places of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as in the firſt of <hi>Saint Iohns</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, where it is ſayd, that that life which was the light of man ſhined in darkneſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 1.5.</note> but darkneſſe was not able to comprehend it that was man. <hi>Saint Paul</hi> thereof draweth an exhortation in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Epheſians</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5 8.</note> to perſwade the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of life, that foraſmuch as they were ſometime in darkneſſe, meaning before their conuerſion, and receiuing of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of Chriſt, now being light, being illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated by the ſpirite of God through the preaching of his worde, therefore they ſhould walke as the children of light. And in the ſecond to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6.</note> ſetting foorth the power and efficacie of the word he ſetteth downe, that as God in the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the worlde, commaunded the light to ſhine out of darkneſſe, ſo hath he ſhined in the heartes of his miniſters, to giue the light of the knowledge of the glorie of god in the face of Ieſus Chriſt. Where the compariſon is to be noted, which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle maketh, that as God in the beginning of the worlde, created light out of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſo hath he done in the hearts of his
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:26495:8"/> miniſters, that by the preaching of the Goſpell, that light might ſhine to others to lighten them, that they might ſée the glorie of God in Chriſt. Wherefore euen as before God ſayde: <hi>Let there be light,</hi> there was no light, but méere darkneſſe, euen ſo before God worke in vs by his word and ſpirite, there is nothing in vs, but méere ignorance and darkeneſſe, no light to behold the glorie of God in Chriſt. No marueile therefore if <hi>Saint Paul</hi> being called to preach the Goſpell do tel <hi>Agrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa</hi> the King,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 26.18.</note> that God hath called him to open their eyes, that they may turne from darkneſſe to light, and from the power of Satan vnto God, or if <hi>Saint Peter</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the doctrine of the Prophets as vnto a light that ſhineth in a darke place,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19.</note> and compare the preaching of the Goſpel vnto the dawning of the day, and the day ſtarre ariſing in our heartes. Hereby may it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, what wee ought to iudge of our ſelues to be nothing but ignorance &amp; dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to be voide of all light &amp; knowledge of Chriſt, vntill by the working of his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite he openeth him ſelfe vnto vs. Before which time as <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifieth, wee walke
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:26495:8"/> as the Gentiles in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vanitie of our minde,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.17.</note> hauing our vnderſtanding darkened, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtraunger from the life of God, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the ignorance in vs, becauſe of the hardneſſe of our heartes. Thus vſeth the Spirite of God, to paynt out the eſtate of man, before God beginneth to worke our regeneratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to aſcribe ignorance &amp; blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vnto our mindes, dulneſſe and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vnto our heartes, yea, and that a ſtonie hardneſſe, as appeareth by <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi> 11.19</note> where he promiſeth that in mercie hee will take away our ſtonie heartes. And vnder the perſon of the Iewes <hi>Eſaye</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 48.4.</note> ſayeth, that wee are all obſtinate, that our neckes are as Iron ſinewes and our browes as browes of braſſe, that is not flexible vnto the yoke of Gods commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and paſt all ſhame to commit wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe. Therefore the holy Ghoſt, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing the corruption of our nature doth terme vs not onely ſicke, weakened or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with ſinne, but euen to be dead in ſinne. For ſo <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> wher hee ſetteth out the grace of Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.1.</note> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that hee hath quickened vs that were dead in treſpaſſes and ſinnes.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:26495:9"/>
            <p>And in like manner, in the ſeconde to the <hi>Coloſsians:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Coloſſ</hi> 13</note> that vs which were dead in ſinnes, and in the vncircumciſion of our fleſh, hath he quickened togither with him forgiuing our treſpaſſes. Theſe manner of termes and epithetes, whereby it hath pleaſed God in his holy worde, to expreſſe both the vtter want of knowledge, in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of faith, and the corruption of our mindes and manners is diligently to be obſerued by vs, by reaſon of the doctrine of the Romiſh cleargie, who although they teache, that <hi>Adam</hi> through his fall, loſt part of that excellent knowledge of pure and heauenly thinges wherewith he was endewed at his firſt creation, &amp; was greatly wounded both in minde and will thorough his diſobedience, and that nowe he is not able to perceiue &amp; do theſe things which God commaundeth him to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand &amp; practiſe without the helpe of God: yet do they not aſcribe that whole igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and blindneſſe vnto the minde of man, neither yet that deadly wounde of ſinne, whereby all power and abilitie to attaine either to the knowledge of God, or practiſe of righteouſnes, is taken from vs,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:26495:9"/> which by theſe titles of right they ought. Our light with them in heauenly matters is in ſome part darkened, but not cleane put out, our vnderſtanding diminiſhed, but not extinguiſhed, the image of God, it was appaired, but not vtterly defaced, the frée will of man to good, it was wounded &amp; weakened, but not quite taken away. But further we ſay, that our knowldge is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come plaine ignorance, our light, dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, our righteouſneſſe ſinfulneſſe, our libertie and freedome, ſeruitude and bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, the image of God, the image of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, that we are not onely depriued of all goodneſſe, but further defiled with all naughtineſſe, that our former power and abilitie was not onely ſhaken and weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned through the fall of our firſt parentes, but that we are vtterly become vnable &amp; impotent, to knowe or do any good thing, and of all abilitie and readineſſe to commit all ſinne and wickedneſſe. Moſt iuſt then and true is that accuſation wherwith <hi>Paul</hi> chargeth all mankinde in generall,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.10.</note> that there is none righteous no not one, that there is none that vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth none that ſéeketh God, that all are gone out of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:26495:10"/> way, that we are become altogether abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable, that there is none that doth good, no not one, our mouth to be as an open ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre, our tongues to be vſed to deceit, the poyſon of aſpes to be vnder our lippes, our mouth to be full of curſing and bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, our feete to be ſwift to ſhed blood, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but calamitie and deſtruction to bée in our wayes, that we know not the waye of peace, no feare of God to be before oure eyes. Thus it is apparant what the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> thought both of Iew and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, and in them of all men conſidered in himſelfe, to be corrupt abhominable with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out vnderſtanding, and thereof he conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth he could not be iuſtifyed by the lawe, but by faith in Ieſus Chriſt. So that eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent it is, ſauing to him that will not know how the ſpirit of God hath in general moſt plainely and ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tifully depriued the whole progenie of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all knowledge of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all goodneſſe, yea of all abilitie to attaine therevnto, yet for our further aſſurance herein, &amp; that this thing may be yet more manifeſt and cleare vnto vs, the holy ghoſt hath not only in this generall ſort, as I ſay in the beginning taught this doctrine, but
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:26495:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> hath euen in particular ſo denyed that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, as it cannot but compel euery man to confeſſe the truth therof. For to the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining or doing of any thing ther be thrée things requiſite, the minde to thinke and conceiue it, the will to atchiue it, and the execution thereof. And if any of theſe points be wanting, what can be perfour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med or done by vs, but neither to doe, nor to will, neither yet to thinke, lyeth in our power, how farre are we therefore from hauing power or abilitie, either to come to the knowledge of Chriſt, or to do any good thing. The firſt, Chriſt himſelfe witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth in the firſt of <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 15.5.</note> 
               <hi>Sine me nihil pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis facere, <hi>without mee ye are able to doe nothing. Saint Auguſtine</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">August. in Ioan.</note> weigheth &amp; preſſeth theſe wordes notably: <hi>Non enim (inquit) ſine me difficulter potestis &amp;c.</hi> Chriſt ſaith <hi>Auſtine: ſaith, not without mee ye can hardly do any thing, neither ſaid he without me ye cannot abſolue, or finiſh any thing, or doe any matter of great weight, but he ſaith ſimply without mee ye can do nothing.</hi> The power there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to do any thing is flatly denyed man in this place by the iudgement of that aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:26495:11"/> and learned father. In like manner to will any thing, lyeth not in vs, but it commeth by the operation and working of Gods ſpirit. So teſtifieth the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in the ſecond to the <hi>Philippians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Philip,</hi> 2.13.</note> it is God which worketh in vs both the will and the déede, and that euen of his good pleaſure, that is of his méere mercie and good will toward vs. If by the giftes and power of nature we were able to do this, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle would not aſcribe it to the particular operation of God, eſpecially in them that be iuſtified. But yet further what ſéemeth more frée and at our libertie then thought, yea, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that alſo is denyed vs, for to think any good thing, lyeth not in vs. So ſayeth the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in the ſeconde to the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinths:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>We are not ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of our ſelues, to thinke any thing as of our ſelues, but all our ſufficiencie is of God.</hi> Wherfore, if both in generall ſort, the ſcripture thus determineth the naturall man to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but darkneſſe, that in him there is no vnderſtanding, that his heart is as hard as a ſtone, that of himſelfe he is dead in ſinne and vnrighteouſnes, that he is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to perceiue thoſe things, which apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:26495:11"/> to the ſpirite of God, that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not once enter into his heart or minde: but alſo in particular ſort doth denye him the power to do, to will, or to think any thing, we may well conclude againſt the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, Pelagians, and Papiſtes with our Sauiour Chriſt, that fleſh &amp; bloud hath not reueiled either to <hi>Peter,</hi> or to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the children of God, neither yet can do, either in whole or in parte, that Chriſt is the liuing God, which confeſſion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth the ſumme of Chriſtian religion. What then is the true and perfect cauſe of this knowledge, whenſoeuer we attaine thereunto, that is expreſſed alſo vnto vs by Chriſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Euangeliſt, to be God, who openeth &amp; reuealeth this vnto vs: for as he denyeth it to fleſh and bloude, ſo doeth he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the cauſe thereof to his Father which is in Heauen. For confirmation whereof although many, I may ſaye in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite teſtimonyes may bee brought out of the holye Scriptures, yet for that the declaration of the former poynte, hath beene the proofe of this in ſo cleare a matter, it ſhal be ſufficient to auouche one or two manifeſt places, for the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:26495:12"/> further eſtabliſhing thereof. Among other, that which is ſayde by <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> muſt néedes moſt manifeſtly, and clearely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and proue this point. For the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſhewing what great mercies and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites he would beſtowe vpon his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, he promiſeth a newe heart will I giue you, a newe ſpirit wil I put within you, &amp; I will take the ſtonie heart out of your bodie, and will giue you an heart of fleſh. And I will put my Spirite within you, and cauſe you to walk in my ſtatutes, and ye ſhall éepe my iudgements and doe them.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi> 36, 26</note> In which wordes <hi>Ezechiel</hi> attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buteth the whole worke of our regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vnto the gift of God, he it is that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth away that olde &amp; ſtonie heart, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are giuen to all iniquitie, and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe from giuing eare vnto any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of God, &amp; he giueth a newe heart, an heart of fleſh, whereby we become apt to receiue the commaundements of God, &amp; a new ſpirite, which leadeth vs, both to the knowledge of the will of God, and to the obedience thereof. Likewiſe <hi>Moſes</hi> in <hi>Deuteronomie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 36.6.</note> ſetting foorth the great goodneſſe of God to his people <hi>Iſrael,</hi> he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribeth
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:26495:12"/> the circumciſion of the heart to the operation and working of the Lorde. For God promiſeth, that if they returne vnto him, and obey his voice, the Lord God ſhal circumciſe their heartes, and the heart of their ſéede after them, that they may loue the Lorde their God with all their heart, with all their ſoule. And to conclude this matter which néedeth no further proofe, that which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Euangeliſt <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in the firſt of his Goſpell,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 1.12.</note> howe ium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth it with this that our Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geliſt affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth here, and how euidently doth it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme both thoſe pointes wee haue hereto ſtoode vpon, where he aſſereth that ſuch as receiued Chriſt &amp; beléeued in his name, were borne not of bloud, nor of the wil of fleſh, nor of the will of man but of God. By which words both the knowledge of Chriſt, and the beléeuing in his name is denyed to man, &amp; giuen to God alone. The verie worde <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> vſed here of our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſt, being well weyed doth ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently argue, that all heauenly things are hid from vs, vntil they be opened and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted by God. For this word being at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed vnto God, doth ſignifie a reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:26495:13"/> by him of ſuch things as were quite before hidden fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our knowledge &amp; vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. Now if this general doctrin ſhall be proued by particular example,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.30.</note> what can be required for the further certaintie and truth hereof. <hi>Moſes</hi> in the <hi>29.</hi> of <hi>Deut.</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braideth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> for their obliuio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; forgetfulnes of the graces &amp; mercies god had ſhewed them in the land of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> yet therwithal he there noteth, that they could not take any profit by theſe things but tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the working &amp; goodnes of God. Ye haue ſeen, ſayth <hi>Moſes,</hi> al that the Lord did before your eyes in the land of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> vnto <hi>Pharao</hi> &amp; vnto al his ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, &amp; vnto al his land. The great temptations which thine eyes haue ſéen thoſe great miracles &amp; won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, yet the Lorde hath not giuen you an heart to perceiue, &amp; eyes to ſée, and eares to heare vnto this day. And in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>13.</hi> of <hi>Math.</hi> Chriſt hauing taught many things by pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rables, his diſciples came to him and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded why he ſpake thus in parables, he made anſwere,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.30.</note> becauſe it is giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to you, to know the ſecrets of the kingdom of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, but to them it is not giuen, therefore ſpeak I vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in parables becauſe they
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:26495:13"/> ſéeing do not ſée, &amp; hearing they heare not, neither vnderſtand &amp;c. Thus we ſée how y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> although they ſaw y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great wonders &amp; miracles, which God did for them in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding they reap no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie therby, becauſe the Lorde did not open their eyes to behold them to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, neither yet their eares to attende vnto ſuch things, or their hart &amp; mind to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiue the goodnes of God, &amp; obedience &amp; thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, which they ought to perfourme vnto God therfore. The diſciples of Chriſt, they vnderſtood the doctrine of Chriſt, they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited &amp; encreaſed in knowledge therby, but why or by what meanes? becauſe to them it was giuen to knowe the ſecretes of the kingdom of God. The Iewes they were not able to perceiue the doctrine of Chriſt, they learned nothing therby, but rather be came more blind &amp; obſtinate, the reaſon is added, becauſe to them it is not giuen. So that it wholy dependeth vpon the gift of God. <hi>Cleophas</hi> and the other diſciple in the <hi>24.</hi> Chapter of <hi>Luke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 24.27.45.</note> when Chriſt ouertooke them going to <hi>Emaus,</hi> although Chriſte rebuked them for their ſlowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in beléeuing all that the Prophetes
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:26495:14"/> had ſpoken. And accompanying them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan at <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted vnto them in all the Scriptures the thinges which were written of him, yet were their eyes ſo holden that they knewe him not, whome before they had often ſéene, neither yet vnderſtood they the Scriptures vntill ſuch time as God o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened their eyes and vnderſtanding both to knowe him and vnderſtande the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Euen as the diſciples of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt had no knowledge, no vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding vntill God gaue it them: ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth it with all the reſt of the children of God, heare they neuer ſo much his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles preache, yea, Chriſt himſelfe perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally ſounding in their eares: yet except the Lorde open our heartes and mindes, as he did <hi>Lydia</hi> the ſicke womans in the Actes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 16.14.</note> it auayleth not one iot, wherefore fleſh and bloud reuealeth not Chriſt vnto vs, but our Father which is in heauen. It remayneth nowe wée weight and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, what commoditie and profite wée ought to reape by this doctrine, &amp; to what vſe it ought to ſerue vs. Firſt, if God be the authour and fountaine and ſole giuer
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:26495:14"/> of all knowledge, faith and all other hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly gifts, it muſt kindle in vs, an earneſt and feruent deſire to prayer, to deſire him to giue vs knowledge and fayth, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, for that otherwayes we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not attaine therevnto. The conſideration of this heretofore, hath moued the ſaintes of God, to be feruente in prayer vnto al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God for the obtaining of theſe gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Among others, how often and how ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently doth the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> praye for this at Gods hands, as in the <hi>119</hi> Pſal.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1 19, 18.27, 33, 34, 35, 36.</note> Open thou mine eies O Lord, that I may ſee the wondrous things of thy law, make me to vnderſtand the way of thy comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, ſo ſhall I talke of thy wondrous workes. And againe: Teach me O Lorde the way of thy ſtatutes, and I ſhall keepe it vnto the end, giue me vnderſtanding, and I ſhall kéepe thy law, make me to goe into the path of thy commaundements, encline my hart to thy teſtimonies, &amp;c. and in the <hi>51.</hi> Pſalme,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 51.</note> that God would make him a cleane heart, and renew a right ſpirit with in him, that he would throughly waſh him and clenſe him from his ſinne. And the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> prayeth not onlye for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:26495:15"/> but for the Churche of the Epheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 1.16, 17.18.</note> that the GOD of our Lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte, the father of glory might yéeld vnto them the ſpirite of wiſedome and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, through the knowledge of him that the eyes of their vnderſtanding maye bée lightened, that they maye knowe the hope of his calling, and what the riches of his glorious inheritaunce is in the Saintes. Theſe thinges as the opening of the eyes, the vnderſtanding of the waye of Gods commaundementes, the making vs to goe in the path of them, the creating of a cleane hearte, the renewing of a righte ſpirite, the clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of ſinne, the inclination of oure heartes to his teſtimonies, they woulde not haue craued ſo conſtantlye at Gods hande, by earneſt and humble prayer if they had not bene perſwaded they came onelye from him, to be his méere giftes. Secondlye, as the meditation of this oughte to make vs to praye to obtayne, ſo hauing atteyned by his goodneſſe to anye of theſe benefites, it ſhoulde ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite vs alſo to thankefulneſſe after the example of all Gods Children, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:26495:15"/> of our Sauioure Chriſte, who giueth thankes to his father Lorde of heauen and earth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.20</note> becauſe he had hid his goſpell from the wiſe and men of vnderſtanding, and had opened it to babes. Thirdelye ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing receyued anye lighte of knowledge and graces of GOD, wée muſt haue a greate care in vſing them to encreaſe his giftes in vs, to prouoke God through our thankefulneſſe to beſtowe his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyes in moſte humble manner vppon vs.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.12.</note> For whoſoeuer hath, to him ſhall bee giuen, but whoſoeuer hath not, from him ſhall bee taken awaye, euen that whiche hée hath, it cannot, neyther oughte it to ingender ſloothfulneſſe in vs, becauſe GOD giueth and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth all in all: for moſte true and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent is that warning which Saynte <hi>Auguſtine</hi> giueth in his Booke <hi>De correp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione &amp; gratia.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reptio: &amp; gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia. cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Non ſe itaque fallant qui di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunt, vt quid nobis predicatur, &amp;c.</hi> That is: Let not (ſayth <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) them deceiue themſelues, who ſaye, Wherefore is it preached and taughte vs, to eſchew euill, and to doe good, if wee doe it not, but it be GOD which worketh in vs, both the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:26495:16"/> will and the deede, but rather let the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full know that <hi>they are led with the ſpirit of God, that they may doe, that they ought to doe, and when they haue done it, they may giue thanks to him that cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them, for they are driuen to the ende they ſhould endeuour to worke, not that they ſhould doe nothing themſelues.</hi> Fourthly, and laſt of all this putteth vs in minde of our owne want and imperfection of our blindneſſe and ignoraunce, wherby we are driuen to acknowledge our owne miſerye, to humble our ſelues before the Lorde, to prayſe God in his giftes, we ſée in our brother, and not to contemn and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe them whome we ſée to want, nor to be proude and loftie for any thing in vs, but to geue the whole praiſe and glorye to God alone. Thus noteth <hi>Auguſtine</hi> verye well in his booke <hi>De bono perſeuerantiae. Cap. <hi>63</hi> &amp; <hi>6,</hi> Nos volumus, ſed Deus operatur in nobis velle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. de bono perſcue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantiae. cap. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3</hi> &amp; <hi>6</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>nos operamur, ſed Deus operatur in nobis, &amp;c.</hi> that is: We will, but God wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in vs to will, we doe, but God wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in vs the déed after his good pleaſure, this is profitable for vs to beleeue and to ſay, that is godly and true, that our confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:26495:16"/> may be humble and lowly, &amp; the whole may be giuen to God, and in his ſixte chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the ſame booke he ſayth, <hi>Tutiores vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uimus ſi totum Deo damus, non autem nos illi ex parte, &amp; nobis ex parte committimus,</hi> wée liue or deale the ſafelier if we giue the whole to God, and not partlye to him, and partly to our ſelues. The Apoſtle S. <hi>Paule</hi> hereof beateth downe the pride and vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorye of the Corinthian Doctors in that whatſoeuer they had they had receiued it of God. For ſo he reaſoneth,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4, 7.</note> What haſt thou that thou haſt not receiued, if thou haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, why reioyceſt thou as though thou hadſt not receiued it? If the knowledge of this doctrine, work theſe effects in vs, then ſhall we haue learned this leſſon, that Chriſt here teacheth vs, to good purpoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe it ſhall auaile vs no more then to ſée the meate whereof we may not féede, ſhall nouriſh our bodies, or to beholde the gold which we may not vſe, ſhal ſerue our turne. To conclude, on this part one onelye caueat is to be giuen, that we take héede, that we abuſe not this doctrine and maner of ſpéeche, as the Euthuſiaſts, Anabaptiſts, and the family of Loue, to the contemning
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:26495:17"/> or neglecting of the preaching of the word of God, who for as muche as here and in diuerſe places beſides, it is ſayde that God reuealeth the miſteries of his kingdom vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, and worketh all things by his holye ſpirit, therof haue they condemned the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call preaching of the word, and haue fled to priuat inſpirations, &amp; reuelatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, dreames, and fantaſies, whereby they haue ben lead into diuers dangerous hereſies. But wée muſt this learn &amp; vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that although god reueleth his wil vnto vs, and worketh both knowledge &amp; fayth by his holy ſpirit, yet doth hee it not, but by that meanes hee hath appointed, that is by the miniſterie of his word, and therefore <hi>Eſai</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſai.</hi> 59.21.</note> the Prophet ioineth in the promiſe of God made, both the word and the ſpirite together. My ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite that is vpon thée, and my words which I haue put in thy mouth, ſhall not departe out of thy mouth, of thy ſéed, nor out of the mouth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſéed of thy ſéede (ſayth the Lord) from henceforth for euer. Where we ſée he ioyneth both y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word &amp; the ſpirit together, they are not to be ſundered. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> plainly teacheth to the <hi>Romains,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.14.17.</note> that no man can beleeue in him of whome hee
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:26495:17"/> hath not heard, and that they cannot heare without a preacher, that faith commeth by hearing, and hearing by the worde of God. And in the <hi>4</hi> to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe</hi> 4.10.</note> he teſtifieth, that when Chriſt aſcended vp into heauen, he led captiuitie captiue, &amp; gaue gifts vnto men, that he therefore gaue ſome to be A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, ſome prophets, and ſome Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, &amp; ſome paſtors, and teachers, to what end? he expreſſeth it to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> gathering togither of the ſaints, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> work of the miniſtery, &amp; for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> building vp of the body of Chriſt. If beléefe &amp; faith in him cannot come but by hearing the word of god preached, &amp; his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters in his church be appointed by him, that the ſaints might haue all thinges ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie to the edifying of the bodye of Chriſt, what impietie is in theſe Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſticall ſpirites eyther to condemn or neglect this ſo excellent not only an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but euen the ſole ordinarye meanes God hath appointed to his church, to work our ſaluation. <hi>Paul</hi> in the <hi>5</hi> to the <hi>Theſſalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.19.</note> giueth warning that we quench not the ſpirit, but therewithal he ioyneth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we deſpiſe not prophecying, he himſelf though he was rapte vp vnto the thirde Heauen,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:26495:18"/> where he hearde wordes which cannot bée ſpoken,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.2.</note> which are not poſſible for man to vtter, yet did he not therefore broche anye new reuelations or dreames, but confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med his doctrine by the teſtimonie of the law and the Prophets. He exhorteth his ſcholer <hi>Timothie</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.13.</note> to giue attendance vnto reading, to exhortation, to doctrine, to lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and to continue therein to ſaue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and them that ſhould heare him. God reuealed vnto Peter and the reſt of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, that he was the ſonne of the liuing God, but by preaching ſo vnto Cleophas and the other Diſciple going to <hi>Emaus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 24.45.</note> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding the Law and the Prophets, hée opened the doctrine of his paſſion. God ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the heart of <hi>Lidia,</hi> conuerted her vnto Chriſtianitie, but by <hi>Paules</hi> miniſterie. Wherefore although God reuealeth all thinges,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 16.14.</note> yet is not the ſpirite to be ſeuered from the word, neither yet the word from the ſpirite, God doth vſe both theſe inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ioyntly. And thus much for the firſt part.</p>
            <p>The ſecond point I ſayd we had to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider was, what the foundation and rocke is, wherevpon the Church of God is builte
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:26495:18"/> for that is expreſſed in the <hi>18</hi> verſe. Thou art <hi>Peter,</hi> and vpon this rock I will builde my Church, and the gates of hel ſhal not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome it. Concerning the true meaning and ſence of theſe wordes, what it is that Chriſt appointeth to be that rock, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon he will build his Church, there is no ſmall variance betwéen vs and the church of Rome. We according to the tenor of the reſt of the ſcriptures, and circumſtance of the place affirme, that Chriſt by this word <hi>Petra</hi> a Rocke, meaneth that whiche <hi>Peter</hi> confeſſed, whiche was Chriſte himſelfe. But the Popiſhe Cleargie to eſtabliſhe the authoritie of the Biſhop of Rome, and his ſuperioritie, power and dominion ouer all other churches, hath applied this ſaying of our Sauioure Chriſt vnto <hi>Peter</hi> alone, making him that Rocke, whereof Chriſt here ſpeaketh, againſt which the gates of Hell cannot preuaile, affyrming that Chriſt in this place hath giuen by theſe wordes a certayne chiefetie and prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence to <hi>Peter</hi> aboue all other Apoſtles, and made him the foundation and heade of his church here in earth and his vicar ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall for the gouernmente thereof, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duing
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:26495:19"/> him with eſpeciall power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie aboue all others. Whiche ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition as alſo Article of Religion, to bee moſt vntrue being the mayne poſte of their religion, and ſuche an Article of fayth, the whiche who beléeueth not, (as they ſaye) cannot bée ſaued, and this place being vſed of them all, eſpeciallye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all others, as the cheefeſt for the confirmation of the Supremacye, and authoritie of the Biſhop of Rome: it ſhall not bee amiſſe, being apparante ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens this Progreſſe, that howſoeuer this Doctrine hath bene heretofore bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten downe, that notwithſtanding it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayneth rooted in many mens mindes, it ſhall be expedient to ſhew and declare this their interpretation to be erroneous, and their collection vaine and friuolous. Which I will doe firſt by the very words and circumſtaunce of the place. Secondly by that, this their expoſition is contrarye to the expreſſe wordes of the Scripture, and rules of Fayth. Thirdely, by the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion and practiſe of the Apoſtles. And laſt of all by the iudgement, and interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the antient and learned Fathers,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:26495:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> and practiſe of their age. Firſte, that euen the verye wordes of the Texte do argue, that when Chriſt ſayth vppon this Rocke I will builde my Church, by this worde <hi>Petra</hi> a Rocke, hée meaneth not the perſon of <hi>Peter</hi> the Apoſtle, but that which <hi>Peter</hi> confeſſed, which was Chriſte it maye appeare by this in that it pleaſed the holye Ghoſte, the Euangeliſt ſhoulde alter and chaunge the name <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> into <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> when as hee mighte haue vſed the ſelfe ſame worde to expreſſe that their mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to make <hi>Peter</hi> the Rock wherevp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he would build his church, for although the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> doe agrée in ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in that both of them by interpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth ſignifi a ſtone or rock: yet the alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp; cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word in propriety of ſpéech &amp; termination in gender, &amp; in conſtruction of perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth import that the holy ghoſt by theſe diuerſe words would mean a diuers thing. For the one word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is <hi>nomen atti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum,</hi> after the proprietie of the Attike tongue, the other <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is <hi>nomen communis linguae,</hi> after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> propriety of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vulgar to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gue, the one word is the maſculine gender, the other the feminine, the perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>truction
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:26495:20"/> differeth, for from the ſecond perſon he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to the third, he ſaith not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thée <hi>Peter,</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> vpon this rock By this varietie and change it is plain the Euangeliſt ment to expreſſe ſome diuerſe thing, otherwiſe it néeded not to haue made any alteration at all, there is no doubte therefore but the holye ghoſt vpon pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, did alter and chaunge the worde <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> into <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> euen to auoyde that erroure that mighte bée gathered thereof, if Chriſte woulde haue taughte vs in this place ſo weightye an Article of oure Fayth, as that is, (as they make it,) that <hi>Peter</hi> muſte bée the Heade of the Churche, vppon whome excepte wée bée builte we cannot bée ſaued, hée woulde not in declaration thereof, ſo haue va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried from his ordinarie name hée gaue him, ſéeing it mighte ſo well haue ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the turne, and by whiche hée mighte playnely haue declared this grounde of Fayth. Wherefore by the worde <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is meante not the Perſon of <hi>Peter,</hi> but Chriſte, whome <hi>Peter</hi> confeſſed and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeued on. For whiche cauſe <hi>Peter</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatelye before in the former verſe,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:26495:20"/> was pronounced bleſſed by our ſauioure Chriſte, for that GOD had opened and reuealed vnto him, that Chriſte was the ſonne of the liuing GOD, and further for the knowledge and beleefe hereof, hée did not onely terme him bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but hée alſo gaue him another name, that whereas before hée was called <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Bar Iona,</hi> hée ſhoulde nowe bée named <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is a Rocke, according as hée had promiſed in the firſte of <hi>Iohn,</hi> becauſe hée knewe and beléeued in the Rocke, vpon whiche not onlye hée, but the whole Churche of GOD ſhoulde bee builte. For hée was ſo named of Chriſt, not becauſe hée ſhoulde bée <hi>Petra</hi> the rock, wherevppon the Congregation of God ſhoulde bée builded, but hée was called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> becauſe hee was builte vpon that Rocke whereon the Churche ſhould be founded. <hi>Petra</hi> whiche is the Rocke (as <hi>Auguſtine</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. ſerm. <hi>21.</hi> de verbo domini.</note> ſayth) hath not his name of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> but <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>Petra</hi> the Rocke, as Chriſt hath not his name of a Chriſtian, but a Chriſtian of Chriſte,<note place="margin">Ierom in <hi>8.</hi> Math.</note> and Sainte <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> affirmeth that <hi>Peter</hi> had his name of <hi>Petra,</hi> whiche is Chriſt, whiche name
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:26495:21"/> agréeth not onely to the perſon of <hi>Peter,</hi> but vnto all Chriſtians and faythfull people, which beléeue in this Rocke, and hold the ſame fayth and confeſſion <hi>Peter</hi> did. Whoſoeuer confeſſeth and beléeueth that Chriſt is the ſonne of the liuing God, as he did, is a <hi>Peter.</hi> Therfore <hi>Ierome</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſixt of <hi>Amos,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierom in <hi>6.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos. Origen. tract. <hi>1.</hi> in Math.</note> termeth al Chriſts A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles <hi>Peters:</hi> And <hi>Origen</hi> plainly teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth, that if we affirme and confeſſe that Chriſt is the ſonne of the liuing God as <hi>Peter</hi> did, then are we <hi>Peters,</hi> and ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the ſame felicitie that he hath obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned becauſe our confeſſion and beléefe is al one, and againe in the ſame place, if wee confeſſe Chriſt to be the ſonne of the liuing god, the father reuealing it vnto vs, it ſhal bee ſayd of eche one of vs, thou art <hi>Peter,</hi> and vpon thee will I build my congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, euery man is <hi>Petra</hi> a Rock, that is, a follower of Chriſt. Thus muche <hi>Origen,</hi> By whome it is playne that <hi>Peter</hi> was ſo named becauſe of the Rock he beléeued in, not for that hée was to be the foundation of the church: and that alſo, that name to be tearmed a rocke is not agréeable to <hi>Peter</hi> alone, but vnto all the faithfull,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:26495:21"/> and no maruaile, for it is an vſuall thing for the properties of Chriſte to be attributed to all his children, as chriſte is called a ſtone, ſo are his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and ſeruauntes named lyuelye ſtones by participation, as they are the lighte of the worlde, and ſalte of the earth, becauſe the ſalt and lighte that they haue is deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and procéedeth from him. And as wée are called righteous, becauſe chriſte is our righteouſneſſe and wiſedome, ſo are wée tearmed Rockes becauſe by him we are ſo made, being the true, perfecte and ſounde Rocke. Wherefore if <hi>Peter</hi> be pronounced bleſſed, onely becauſe of the confeſſion hée made, and that his name was chaunged from <hi>Simon</hi> vnto <hi>Peter,</hi> for that cauſe alone, and that his name agreeth to all chriſtians, who holde and make the ſame confeſſion hée did, as well as vnto him, then is it apparante by the order and Sequel of the Texte, and truth of the matter, that the Rocke whereon chriſte will builde his churche, is not the perſon of <hi>Peter,</hi> no more then it is the perſon of anye other Apoſtle, but that whereby both <hi>Peter,</hi> and other
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:26495:22"/> faythfull, ſhall be come both bleſſed and <hi>Peters.</hi> For if wee marke the order and courſe of the Dialogue betweene Chriſt, and his Diſciples firſt wee may obſerue, that the Queſtion is propounded not to <hi>Peter</hi> alone, but generallye vnto all, whome doe ye ſaye that I am. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, Chriſt demaunded not what they thought of Peter, but what they thoughte of him, ſo that in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſpect we cannot ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine any eſpeciall thing ment, and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded toward <hi>Peter</hi> more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any other. For in that he made aunſwere alone, that was in the perſon of them all, to auoide confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and declare vnitie,<note place="margin">Cyprianus de ſimpli. praelat. Auguſt. ſerm. <hi>21.</hi> de verbo domini.</note> as <hi>Ciprian</hi> ſayth, he was but their mouth, So alſo <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith <hi>Petrus ſaepe vnus reſpondit pro omnibus, &amp;c. <hi>Peter oftentimes made aunſwere for all, the Lord aſking and ſaying whome ſay ye that I am, Peter anſwered, Thou art the ſonne of the liuing god, he only gaue an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere for many, to declare vnity in many.</hi>
               </hi> And what was the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Peter,</hi> it was that Chriſt was the ſon of the liuing God, this confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was approued &amp; commended of Chriſt, not the perſon of <hi>Peter,</hi> but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the confeſſion, herewithall if wee
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:26495:22"/> marke what happened immediatly after the concluſion of the dialogue vnto <hi>Peter,</hi> nothing can be more plaine than that <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> cannot be that rocke whereupon God will build his Church, for that rocke muſt be ſuch againſt which the gates of hell can not preuaile, how can <hi>Peter</hi> then be that foundation, who immediatly after this confeſſion fell ſo grieuouſly, that he was termed of our Sauiour Chriſt, Satan. For <hi>Peter</hi> diſwading him from going vp to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> to accompliſh the worke of our redemption, he ſaide vnto him, away from mée Satan, thou ſauoureſt not the things that are of God, but the things that are of men. And afterwarde he denyed &amp; abiured his Maſter, he was farre there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore from being that vnmouable rocke, which could not be ſhaken, ſuch an one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which the gates of hell could not preuaile, ſo then to conclude this pointe, if the change and alteration of the word and conſtruction may argue the meaning of a diuerſe thing, when otherwiſe the ſelfe ſame worde might haue better and plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyer declared that ſo weightie and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie an article of our faith, as they make
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:26495:23"/> that is of <hi>Peters</hi> ſupremacie, if the bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>Peter</hi> and the name be obtained of Chriſt, and that the ſame be not only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to <hi>Peter,</hi> but vnto all who ſhal in like manner lay holde vpon that rocke and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the ſame faith, if the whole courſe of the dialogue be directed not to know <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> opinion alone, but of them all, what they thought, not of <hi>Peter,</hi> but of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt, and to confirme them in that firme and ſtedfaſt faith, they had in him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all troubles and perſecutions, that ſhould after enſue, and with all to haue a publike teſtimonie of them all, that they had a better and truer opinion of him, then the common multitude, if the rocke wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Gods Church muſt be founded, muſt be ſuch an one as cannot be ſhaken by any force and ſubtiltie of Satan, and <hi>Peter</hi> as hath appeared, was ſo weakened at di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe times, that he was ouercome almoſt for euer. I may well ſaye, that euen the wordes, and circumſtance of the place, doth euict that <hi>Peter</hi> is not made that <hi>petra</hi> the rocke vpon the which the Church is to be built. But yet that this may be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of doubt, if we well weigh the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:26495:23"/> of our Romiſh Catholikes, we ſhal finde it to be contrarie to the expreſſe wordes of the Scripture, and the doctrine of the holie Ghoſt in other places, yea, and to the analogie and rules of faith. <hi>Saint Paul</hi> in the <hi>1.</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi>
               </note> finding fault with the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> who were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided by chooſing to themſelues ſundrie doctors and teachers, whome they would heare and followe. Some ſaying I am <hi>Paules,</hi> another, I am <hi>Apollos,</hi> another, I am <hi>Cephas,</hi> &amp; the fourth, I am <hi>Chriſtes,</hi> he flatly ſetteth downe,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11.</note> that <hi>fundamentum aliud nemo ponere potest, preter id quod poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt, Ieſum Chriſtum. <hi>Other foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on can no man lay then that which is laid, which is Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </hi> If onely Chriſt be the foundation and no other: If neither <hi>Paul,</hi> nor <hi>Apollo,</hi> nor <hi>Cephas,</hi> ought to be ſo accompted, how can they challenge this prerogatiue vnto <hi>Peter,</hi> being denyed ſo expreſſely vnto him or vnto any other. <hi>Paul</hi> affirmeth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.22.</note> that GOD had made all things ſubiect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Chriſtes feete, and appointed him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all things the head of the Churche, which is his bodie, and of what kinde of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:26495:24"/> bodie that he declareth alſo in the fifth of the ſame Epiſtle, of his fleſh &amp; his bones, for ſaith he, Chriſt nouriſheth and cheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth his Church,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 5.30.</note> becauſe we are mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of his bodie, fleſh and bones, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if the Church be the bodie of Chriſt, and God hath appointed Chriſt to be the head thereof, and that head be of the ſame nature and ſubſtance, of the ſame fleſh and bone, the reſt of the bodie is: what cauſe is there to make any other head, except we ſhould thinke either that one head not to be ſufficient to giue life, and to rule the bodie, or to be too mightie and of too great rule and authoritie, and therefore do ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyne another thereunto, as when two <hi>Conſuls</hi> or <hi>Caeſares</hi> be created of one place, the one to abridge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> others power and might. But neither of theſe inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences can be feared in Chriſt, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we néede not to aſſigne another head to his bodie. Beſides the head of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church is that part of the bodie which giueth life, nouriſheth and augmenteth the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of the faithfull vnto eternall life, but who doth or can performe this but onely Chriſt? euen as a man cheriſheth his own
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:26495:24"/> fleſh, ſo nouriſheth he the Church which conſiſteth of his own fleſh and bone as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifieth, he therefore is the onely head. There is the ſame reaſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Chriſt and his church, that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene man and wife, as the ſame Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle teſtifieth, for as the huſbande is the wiues head, ſo Chriſt is the head of the church, as the church is in ſubiection to Chriſt: ſo the wiues to their huſbands. As Chriſt loued his church, ſo wiues their huſbands. As wiues are their huſbandes fleſh: ſo is the church the fleſh of Chriſt. So that then, he that is the head of the church is the huſband and ſpouſe thereof. For, therefore he is the head becauſe he is the huſband, but there is but one huſband therefore whoſoeuer ſhall make any other head of the church then Chriſt, muſt alſo make another huſbande, if another huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, then an adulterer and the church an harlot, for one wife cannot haue two bridegromes or huſbandes, <hi>Paul</hi> ſayth of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> I haue prepared you for one huſband, to preſent you a pure virgin to Chriſt, &amp; <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> in the Euangeliſt <hi>Iohn</hi> ſayeth, he is the bridegrome &amp; his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:26495:25"/> be the only miniſters &amp; frinds of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bridegrome, they are only the makers of the mariage betwéen Chriſt &amp; his church. How can <hi>Peter</hi> then be accounted as the head of Gods church, Chriſt himſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the head and the huſband thereof? Let him therefore be eſtéemed as a miniſter, &amp; frinde of the ſpouſe, as Chriſt himſelfe hath termed him and all the reſt of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and no further. And ſurely it is not lightly to be regarded, that after Chriſt had ſaid to <hi>Peter,</hi> thou art <hi>Peter,</hi> and vpon this rocke will I build my church, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they would eſtabliſh a chiefetie &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence giuen him ouer all other the Apoſtles and congregation of God, ariſing this controuerſie among them, which of them ſhould be the greateſt, and that euen then, when he was readie to go to ſuffer, &amp; depart from them, ſuppoſing (as it ſhoulde ſéeme) after the departure of Chriſt, ſome one of them ſhould be chief, and beare rule ouer the reſt: euen then our Sauiour Chriſt beateth downe vtterly, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite and imagination of theirs, ſhewing that rule and ſoueraintie belongeth vnto Kings and Princes. The Kings of the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:26495:25"/> Gentiles they reigne, they beare rule, they are called gratious Lordes. But ye ſhal not be ſo, it ſhal not be ſo among you, whoſoeuer wilbe the chiefe among you, let him be your ſeruaunt, and he ſetteth himſelfe an example before them, that he came not to haue ſeruice done vnto him, but to ſerue, and to giue his life for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of many. Hereby although it were the eſpeciall purpoſe of our Sauiour Chriſt to take away that ambition which reigned in his diſciples by reaſon they dreamed to obtaine by him an earthly and terreſtriall kingdome, notwithſtanding being ſo often occaſioned to declare tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough their deſire of ſoueraintie and rule, and eſpecially before his death &amp; paſſion, whome after his death he would leaue his deputie and vicegerent of whome they ſhould depende and be gouerned, it may giue iuſt occaſion to thinke, that as when he was conuerſant with them in fleſh, he would not giue any ſupremacie or prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence to any one more than to another, but made them all equall, ſo alſo after his aſcenſion he would haue them ſo continue, eſpecially the reaſon of Chriſt being ſuch
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:26495:26"/> as is appliable to the whole courſe of this life. This ſtrife and contention would not haue riſen, if they had knowne at any time Chriſt had appointed <hi>Peter</hi> their chiefe &amp; gouernour, or elſe might eaſily haue béene ended, if aunſwere had béene made by Chriſt, that <hi>Peter</hi> was he who ſhoulde be in his ſtead after his death. But what if this doctrine of theirs be contrary to the groundes of our faith, ſhall we think then their interpretation to be true, if <hi>Peter</hi> be the rocke wheron the church is to be built, then muſt the church alſo beléeue in <hi>Peter,</hi> for the church cannot be built but by faith and beliefe, but to beléeue in <hi>Peter</hi> is to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe that to the creature, which onely is to be yelded vnto the creatour, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it cannot want great impietie to giue this vnto <hi>Peter</hi> which they doe. Beſides the church of God containeth the whole companie of the faithful, euen from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the worlde vnto the ende, why then if <hi>Peter</hi> be the rocke of the whole and vniuerſall church of Chriſt, then muſt the faithfull that were before <hi>Peter</hi> was born be founded vpon <hi>Peter</hi> and depend on him as their head, but to affirme that, I think
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:26495:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> cannot want abſurditie, therefore except you will make euen the viſible church of God to haue had many viſible heads, this their aſſertion muſt prooue but a vaine imagination. If we further call to minde that which <hi>Paul</hi> writeth of <hi>Peter,</hi> that hee was the Apoſtle of the <hi>Iewes</hi> onely, and <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe the Apoſtle of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> can <hi>Peter</hi> be accounted the foundation and head of the vniuerſall church, when as to preach vnto the <hi>Gentiles</hi> belonged not to him? this reaſon driueth <hi>Cardinall Poole</hi> into ſuch ſtreightes, that whereas other of his adherents ſaye, <hi>Peter</hi> was appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted head of the church here, other immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly after his reſurrection, he is compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to ſaye, that <hi>Peters</hi> ſupremacie tooke no place before <hi>Paules</hi> conuerſion, for that before that <hi>Peter</hi> could not repreſent the perſon of Chriſt, and leaue twelue Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles to figure vnto vs the twelue tribes of <hi>Iſraell.</hi> Wherefore theſe things being well weyghed together, firſt, that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle flatly ſetteth downe that no man can, or ought to laye any other foundation then Chriſt himſelfe, the <hi>Corinthians</hi> ſeeking eſpecially to depende vppon ſome one principally, as their cheife teacher, I
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:26495:27"/> denying it to bee lawfull for them to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pende vppon <hi>Cephas</hi> himſelfe, who was <hi>Peter.</hi> Secondly, aſſigning Chriſt the head, the huſband of his bodie the church, his ſpouſe, his wife, in which thinges there can be no communion or fellowſhip. Further, this controuerſie ariſing ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten among his diſciples, who ſhoulde be the chiefeſt, and our Sauiour Chriſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying all ſuperioritie at all times to any of them, neither yet giuing any ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation that <hi>Peter</hi> ſhoulde be their chiefe, no not after his death, and this their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation being ſuch as cauſeth to giue that vnto man which is proper to GOD alone, as faith and beliefe, and to make diuerſe bodies, diuerſe churches, diuerſe heades, diuerſe foundations, when the holye Ghoſte appointeth but one Church, one head, one foundation, and laſt of all the Holye Ghoſte aſſigning vnto <hi>Peter,</hi> the miniſterie of circumciſion onely, wée may iuſtly affirme the expoſition of our Romiſh Cleargie, to be contrarye to the expreſſe worde of GOD and rules of our faith.</p>
            <p>I am not ignorant here of their blinde ſubtilties and diſtinctions, whereby they
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:26495:27"/> would ſhift of the force of theſe reaſons, in making Chriſt <hi>natiuum &amp; reale funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum: <hi>The naturall and ſubſtantiall foundation,</hi>
               </hi> but <hi>Peter <hi>ministeriale fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentum,</hi> the miniſteriall foundation here in earth:</hi> that is, that the miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and office of <hi>Peter</hi> is appoynted of GOD aboue the function of all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Apoſtles, to be that miniſterie wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he will builde his vniuerſall Churche, and gouerne it: vppon whome, and of whome all other Churches muſt hang and depende. Which aſſertion to be moſt vntrue, that any principall authoritie, either for the buylding vp of the Church, or gouernement thereof, was by this place or any other committed vnto <hi>Peter</hi> aboue the other Apoſtles, it may appeare by this that none of the Apoſtles, either in their writings or doinges, hath euer acknowledged any ſuch thing, but the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, accounting him but equall to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, giuing him no preheminence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue his fellowes. For proofe hereof, what can be more manifeſt, than that <hi>Paul</hi> writeth to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.19.</note> where the Apoſtle of purpoſe ſpeaking of the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Church, and their Apoſtolicall
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:26495:28"/> function, ſayeth, that nowe they were no more ſtraungers and forrenners, but citizens with the Saintes, and of the houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde of GOD, and that they were buylt vppon the foundation of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Prophets, Ieſus Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe being the head corner ſtone. By this worde foundation in this place, he mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vndoubtedly the doctrine of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and wee ſee further, that hee ſpeaketh in generall of the Apoſtles in the plurall number, not attributing any thing to any one of the Apoſtles, as to a principall, who ſhoulde be preferred in this buylding before others: and beſides, he hath layde Chriſt, the head corner ſtone, vppon which the doctrine of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and Prophets muſt worke vpon. The ſame Apoſtle in the fourth Chapter of the ſame Epiſtle,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.11.12.</note> deſcribinge what gyftes and functions GOD hath left to his Church, for the building thereof hee ſayeth Chriſt after his aſcention gaue ſome to be Apoſtles, ſome Prophets, ſome Euangeliſtes, ſome Paſtours and teachers, to the gathering together of the Saintes, and buylding of the bodye of Chriſt: but to haue appointed or giuen
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:26495:28"/> any generall and vniuerſall Biſhop, or Paſtour, to that ende, there is not one worde, neither there, nor in the firſt to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> where the Apoſtle de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth the diuerſitie of giftes and functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, GOD hath giuen to his Church.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28</note> Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> in the one and twentéeth of the Reuelation,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21.14.</note> deſcribing heauenly <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> the Church of GOD buylt by the ſimilitude of a Citie, he maketh that the Wall of the citie had twelue founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and in them the names of the lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes twelue Apoſtles. Here wée ſee in this built citie of GOD, nothing is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to <hi>Peter</hi> aboue the reſt, all are made equall, the doctrine of all the Apoſtles is alike, tearmed by the name of foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and haue all ſhare alike in the Walles of the Citie of GOD What cauſe is then why any prerogatiue ſhould bee giuen to <hi>Peter</hi> more then to any other. They ſhall eate and drinke at Gods ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in his kingdome, and ſit and iudge the twelue Tribes of <hi>Iſraell</hi> alike, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by <hi>Luke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.30.</note> which coulde not bee, if principall power were giuen to <hi>Peter</hi> which they ſtriue for, ouer the whole Church.</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:26495:29"/>
            <p>And yet, that this may appeare more manifeſt. Let vs marke that <hi>Paul</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in the <hi>15.</hi> to the <hi>Romanes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.20.</note> where he ſayth, that hee enforceth himſelf to preach the Goſpell, where Chriſt had not beene preached, and why? leaſt, ſayth hee, I ſhoulde haue built vppon an other mans foundation.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.10.</note> And in the firſt to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> he teſtifieth, that according to the grace of GOD giuen vnto him, as a faithfull builder, he had layde the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church of <hi>Corinth.</hi> If <hi>Paul</hi> in diuerſe places did ſo preache the Goſpell, that he might not build vppon an other mans foundation, if the <hi>Corinthians</hi> the buylding of GOD, were founded by <hi>Paules</hi> miniſterie, then <hi>Peters</hi> miniſterie is not neceſſarily the foundation of all Churches, or elſe <hi>Paul</hi> challenged to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe more then he ought. But if none of theſe teſtimonies were extant, the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the <hi>Galathians</hi> were ſufficient to conuince their aſſertion. For it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth there, that diuerſe falſe Prophets, and vaine glorious teachers, went about to deface <hi>Paules</hi> doctrine, and bring him out of credite and his diſciples, ſaying that <hi>Paul</hi> was not ſo excellent an Apoſtle as
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:26495:29"/> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iames</hi> were, and the other A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, that were conuerſant with Chriſt while he liued here vppon earth, that hee was ſince called to bee an Apoſtle, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the other were rather to be followed and belieued than hee, and ſo forth. <hi>Paul</hi> vnderſtanding and perceiuing this, he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth about to prooue, that hee is no whit inferiour to <hi>Peter, Iames,</hi> or anye other the Apoſtles, for that the Goſpell hee taught, hee receiued it not of man, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was hee taught it, but by the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of Ieſus Chriſt.<note place="margin">Gal. <hi>1.</hi> &amp; <hi>2.</hi> Chap.</note> After his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, hee went not of manye yeares to Ieruſalem, to learne any thing of the chiefe Apoſtles, when hee came vp to Ieruſalem, it was to ſee <hi>Peter</hi> onely, and to declare his conſent and agreement in preaching of the Goſpell, becauſe of ſclaunders, not to learne anye thinge of them that ſeemed to bee the chiefeſt Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peter, Iames,</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> ſeeing the Goſpell of vncircumciſion was commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him, as the Goſpell of circumciſion was vnto <hi>Peter,</hi> in that God, which was mightie in the one, was mighty alſo in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they required no ſubmiſſion or obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:26495:30"/> at <hi>Saint Paules</hi> handes, or to doe any homage to any of them, but they gaue vnto him, the right hande of fellowſhip. And further, hee was ſo farre from ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging <hi>Peter</hi> his ſuperiour or bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. That when he came to <hi>Antioche</hi> he withſtoode him and rebuked him to his face, for his diſſimulation, betweene the Iewes and Gentiles. If this be well conſidered, wee may well perceiue that <hi>Paul</hi> accounted not of <hi>Peter,</hi> as of his head, or chiefe of the Church, naming <hi>Iames</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> pillers of the Church as well as hee, and not yelding to him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing aboue him ſelfe.</p>
            <p>In the ſeconde to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.5.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> declareth that he thinketh himſelfe nothing inferiour vnto the chiefeſt Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. <hi>Peter,</hi> in his Epiſtles, he neuer challengeth any ſuperioritie, neither by ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle nor by doctrine, he maketh Chriſt the electe precious and chiefe corner ſtone, and all the faithfull liuing ſtones of the ſpirituall houſe a like, hee claymeth not ciuill gouernement, or that Kinges and Princes ought to bee ſubiect vnto him as the Pope doeth, but commaundeth all Subiectes to bee obedient vnto their
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:26495:30"/> Princes and gouernours, he termeth him ſelfe but <hi>compreſbyterum,</hi> a fellowe elder with the reſt, and exhorteth his fellow mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters not to be as Lordes ouer Gods he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritage, in his whole writing he doth not im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>periouſly commaund, but humbly exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, not to be ouerlong in this, it cannot be thought, that <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles hauing ſo fully and plentiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taught all thinges, appertaining to the Church of God, yea euen the leaſt functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that they would in all their writings haue concealed ſo great, weightie and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie point, as this of <hi>Peters</hi> ſupremacie and one general head vnder Chriſt, for the gouernment of his Church, being ſuche as it is made of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that whoſoeuer acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth it not, cannot be ſaued. Now if this which I haue taughte by the opinion and iudgement of the Apoſtles, ſhall appeare alſo by their practiſe and dealing towarde <hi>Peter,</hi> what can be required further for the ouerthrow of their interpretation. And for a perfect view hereof, let vs but conſider the whole order and manner of the firſte councell holden of the Apoſtles in the <hi>15.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Actor.</hi> 15.5.</note> of the actes: there it is mentioned, that cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine variance and diſſention falling oute
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:26495:31"/> by reaſon ſome of the ſect of the Phariſeis, vrged the obſeruation of circumciſion, and other ceremonies of the law, as neceſſarye to ſaluation, it was determined that <hi>Paule</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> ſhould go vp to the Apoſtles &amp; Elders at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> about this queſtion. At their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming the matter being declared the Apoſtles &amp; Elders aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled together to reaſon of the matter, after much debating, <hi>Peter</hi> aroſe and declared what God had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed vnto him, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning this point, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at <hi>Cornelius</hi> conuerſion. After him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe <hi>Paul</hi> &amp; <hi>Barnabas,</hi> who alſo tolde their opinion, &amp; what God had opened vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Thirdly ariſeth <hi>Iames,</hi> hee approueth the former iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, confirmeth it by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and hauing done ſo, giueth aduiſe to ſend their determination in writing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it was taken &amp; appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, &amp; the Apoſtles and elders, &amp; the whole congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſent choſen men, namely <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas</hi> &amp; <hi>paul,</hi> with their letters. Firſt here is to be obſerued, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is not mentioned that <hi>Peter</hi> ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moned this Councel by his autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, but it is done by the conſent of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and elders, contrary to that prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue the Pope chale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth to himſelfe. <hi>Peter</hi> although he ſpake firſt alone, yet followeth
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:26495:31"/> it not that he was therefore accounted the chéefeſt, for neither ſpake he only and often times in great Councels, the loweſt and yongeſt begin firſt, the eldeſt &amp; head of all ſpeaketh laſt. Secondly, in the aſſemblye after <hi>Peter</hi> had opened his mind, and al the reſt had don, laſt of al, not <hi>Peter,</hi> but <hi>Iames</hi> pronounced the ſentence, whiche belonged to the head and Preſident of the Councell. Thirdly, the Legats &amp; embaſſadors which were ſent, were not appointed by Peter, nor ſent by his authoritie, after the maner of the Pope, but they were choſen by all the Apoſtles and Elders, &amp; the whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, and ſent by them. Fourthly the ſtile of the letter doth argue, they gaue no preheminence to Peter aboue other in this aſſemblie, for thus it runneth: <hi>The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, Elders and Brethren ſend greeting, &amp;c.</hi> For as much as we haue heard, &amp;c. It ſéemed good to vs, when we were come to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, to ſend choſen men to you, &amp;c. it ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med good to the holy ghoſt &amp; vnto vs, to lay no more burthen, &amp;c. Thus we ſée how the whole action is made common to them all equallye, none named, or preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore another, in anye reſpecte, farre diuerſe from the Popes determination,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:26495:32"/> and ſtile of his letters, the tenour of which runneth much otherwiſe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 8.24.</note> Beſides in the eight of the Acts, when the Apoſtles heard that <hi>Samaria</hi> had receiued the Goſpell, the Apoſtles ſent <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> to confirme them, whiche ſending declareth plainelye, that they did not acknowledge him as a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour, and in that he obeieth and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, he declareth himſelfe to bee but their fellow. For be it that <hi>Eckius</hi> ſayth true, that oftentimes the chéefeſt of the company be ſent in matters, yet there is no Senate nor councell that will ſend their chéefe and gouernour. And the ſame Apoſtle in the <hi>11</hi> Acts,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 11.3.</note> being reproued for going to <hi>Corneli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> he excuſeth and cleareth himſelf, giuing a reaſon of that his doing. And of <hi>Paul</hi> in the ſecond to the <hi>Galathians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.11.</note> he was reproo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to his face, for that he was worthye of rebuke, wherefore to conclude, if neither in planting of the church of God, neither in deciding of controuerſies in matters of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, neither in enioyning &amp; commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thinges to be done, neither yet by any title, dutie, ſeruice or ſignification of dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, <hi>Peter</hi> either bare himſelfe, or the reſt receiued him as their head and vniuerſall Biſhop, but contrariwiſe both he vſed him
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:26495:32"/> ſelfe, and they made themſelues equall in all their doings vnto him: I maye iuſtlye conclude that euen the opinion and practiſe of the Apoſtles and primitiue churche, doth manifeſtly conuict the interpretation of the Papiſts in this place, making <hi>Peter</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rock, foundation, and heade of Gods Churche to bée moſt vntrue. This point notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by this I haue already ſaid, it be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently proued, yet for diuers mens further contentation, let vs ſée howe the auntiente and learned Fathers, haue expounded this place, whether by this worde <hi>Petra</hi> they haue vnderſtoode the perſon of <hi>Peter,</hi> or him whom <hi>Peter</hi> confeſſed, whiche was Chriſt. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> in the <hi>55</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſ. hom. <hi>55.</hi> in Mat.</note> Homily vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Mathew,</hi> expoundeth <hi>Petra</hi> to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith and confeſſion. <hi>Super hanc Petram .i. in hac fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de &amp; confeſsione aedificabo eccleſiam,</hi> that is, vppon this Fayth and Confeſſion I will build my Church, and vpon the <hi>32</hi> Pſalm, <hi>Statuit pedes nostros ſuper petram id eſt ſuper fidem, &amp;c</hi> that is he hath ſet our féete vpon the rocke, that is vpon Faith,<note place="margin">Chryſ. ſuper Pſal. <hi>52.</hi>
               </note> for Fayth in <hi>Chriſt may well be called a Rocke which cannot be broken, wherefore when Peter had declared and ſayd, thou art the ſonne of the liuing God, Chriſt immediatelye
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:26495:33"/> added, thou art peter, and vpon this rock I wil build my church.</hi> Thus it is appara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> toke not the perſon of Peter to be that rock here mentioned, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which Peter repoſed his beléefe in. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. <hi>21.</hi> de verbis Dom.</note> in this place writeth thus. <hi>Super hanc Petram qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> confeſſus es, &amp;c.</hi> that is, <hi>vpon this rock which thou haſt confeſſed, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this Rock which thou haſt acknowledged, ſaying thou art the ſon of the liuing God, I will build my congregation, vpon my ſelfe I will build my church, vpon my ſelf I will build the, not my ſelf vpon thee, for they that would haue me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> build vpon me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaid, I hold of <hi>Paul,</hi> another I hold of <hi>Apollo,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother I of <hi>Cephas</hi> which is <hi>Peter,</hi> but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which would not be built vpon <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> but vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the rock, ſaid I hold of Chriſt.</hi> Againe in another place <hi>Super hanc Petram quam confeſſus est aedificabo eccleſiam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem in Ioan. tract. <hi>124.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp;c</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, <hi>vpon this rock which thou haſt confeſſed I wil build my church, for the rocke was Chriſt, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>datio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Peter</hi> himſelfe was built, for other foundation then that which is laid, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lay, which is <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> the church therfore that is founded on <hi>Chriſt,</hi> hath take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the keyes of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of him.</hi> I omit that which
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:26495:33"/> he writeth alſo in his booke againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Iewes Pagans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem contra Iud. Pag. &amp; Arti.</note> and <hi>Adrians</hi> where he alſo expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth this place after this maner. By this it appeareth how he expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded this rock here me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned, not to bee <hi>Peter</hi> but Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. <hi>Gregor. miſſenus</hi> ſaith, <hi>Tu es Petrus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. Miſſe. in teſiim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nijs, delectis ex veteri teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thou art Peter, &amp; vpon this Rock I will build my Church, he meaneth, ſaith he, the confeſſion of Chriſt, for he had ſayd before, thou art the ſonne of the liuing God. And <hi>Hilarius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hilar. lib. <hi>4.</hi> de Trini.</note> 
               <hi>Petra nihil aliud est qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> firma et in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concuſſa diſcipuli fides.</hi> The rock is nothing elſe but the ſtrong and aſſured faith of the Diſciple. What can be plainer then that which <hi>Origen</hi> writeth vpon this place. If wée confeſſe (ſayth he) Chriſte to bee the ſonne of God, the Father reuealing it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, it ſhall be ſayd to ech one of vs, thou art Peter,<note place="margin">Orig. tract. in Math.</note> and vppon this Rocke will I build my Congregation, euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is <hi>Petra</hi> that is a diſciple of Chriſt, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch a rock all eccleſiaſtical learning is builte, if thou thinke that the whole church is only builte vpon Peter, what wilt thou ſaye of <hi>Iohn</hi> the ſonne of thunder, and of the other Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. And further indéede it was ſpoken to Peter, vpon this Rocke I will builde my Congregation: Notwithſtanding,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:26495:34"/> it is ſpoken in like maner of all the other Apoſtles, and to all faithfull and perfite be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are all <hi>Peters,</hi> and Rockes, and vpon al them and the Prophets, is Chriſts Church built, and the gates of hell ſhal not preuayle agaynſt any of them. Wherefore if they will giue credit to <hi>Origen</hi> who was within <hi>235</hi> yeres after Chriſt, that, that which was ſayd to <hi>Peter,</hi> ſhall be ſayde to euery Faithfull man, making the like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and that this which was ſpoken to <hi>Peter</hi> here, was ſpoken to all the Apoſtles, and to all Faithfull and perfite men in like maner. Then is here nothing attributed more vnto <hi>Peter,</hi> then vnto any of the other Apoſtles. <hi>Gregorie</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. lib. <hi>4.33.</hi> Epiſt.</note> was himſelfe Biſhop of Rome, and whome our Romiſh Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie woulde haue to chalenge this dignitie and prerogatiue, they giue vnto <hi>Peter,</hi> hée of this place and diuerſe others which they vſe, as moſte weightie to confirme <hi>Peters</hi> and the Popes Supremacie, inferreth the quite contrary. For he reaſoneth thus, to <hi>Peter</hi> it was ſayde, Loueſt thou me, féede my ſhéepe, Satan hath deſired to ſifte thée, but I prayed that thy Faith may not faile, thou being conuerted, ſtrengthen thy Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, thou art <hi>Peter,</hi> and vpon this Rocke
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:26495:34"/> will I build my church, to thée I will giue the keyes of the kingdome of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, &amp;c. and he concludeth in the ende, notwithſtanding <hi>Peter</hi> is not called Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall Biſhop. This one man hath lefte ſufficient witneſſe behind him to condemn in <hi>Peter,</hi> and in all Biſhops of Rome, both the name of that dignitie and ſuperioritie, and alſo the authoritie and iuriſdiction which the Pope doth claime vnto himſelfe by vertu of this place. For firſt how ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and bitterly writeth he againſt this, that eyther <hi>Iohn</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> or any other Biſhop ſhoulde clayme or tearm himſelf to be the vniuerſall Biſhop of the whole Church in his Epiſtles: Firſt in his fourth booke he tearmeth this Title and name, a new, a proude,<note place="margin">Greg. lib <hi>4.</hi> Epiſt <hi>32.</hi> Ep. <hi>38.</hi> Ep. <hi>39.</hi>
               </note> a pompous name. In his <hi>38</hi> Epiſtle of the ſame booke, a raſh, fooliſh, peruerſe name, a name of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour. In the Epiſtle following, a wicked name, a name of vanitie, a name of Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, a name of blaſphemie.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>epi.</hi> 2.</note> In his ſixte booke and <hi>2</hi> Epiſtle, a puffe of arrogancie and in the <hi>24</hi> Epiſtle of the ſame Booke a ſuperſtitious and vngodly name. So farre then in his iudgement is it from being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gréeable to Gods will, for any Biſhop to
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:26495:35"/> claime this name, that he accounteth it a moſt vngodly and impious thing, and not only the name, of modeſty and humility is thus diſalowed of him, as ſome woulde beare vs in hande, but the very office, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority &amp; iuriſdiction that is claimed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, for otherwiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reaſons he vſeth were of no force,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 4.38.</note> for in the <hi>38</hi> Epiſtle of his <hi>40</hi> Booke hée reaſoneth thus. What anſwere wilt thou make vnto Chriſt, at the trial of the laſt iudgement, that goeſt about vnder the name of an Vniuerſall Biſhop to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due all his members vnto thée. Here he condemneth the name, for that hee whiche deſireth it, goeth aboute to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due all the members of Chriſte vnto him. Whiche in verye déede is broughte to paſſe not by the verye name, but by the power ſignifyed by the name. His Compariſon in the thirtith Epiſtle of the ſame Booke,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Li.</hi> 4.30. <hi>Epi.</hi>
               </note> where he reſembleth him to <hi>Lucifer,</hi> that affecteth the name, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not condemne the name onlye, but the thing alſo, becauſe it was not <hi>Lucifers</hi> deſyre onelye to bee named God, but alſo to ſitte in his ſeate, and execute his Dominion. When as in that place hee ſayeth that <hi>Iohn</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople,</hi>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:26495:35"/> challenging that Title, doeth <hi>Contra Euangelicam Doctrinam</hi> againſt the meaning of the Goſpell, againſt Saint <hi>Peter</hi> the Apoſtle, agaynſte the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of the Canons, agaynſt the faith, agaynſte all the Churches of GOD, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt GOD himſelfe, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thinges more in anye mans iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that maye bée ſufficiente, by his authoritie to diſallow the name, and the office, not onely in <hi>Iohn</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> but alſo in any other Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop that ſhall clayme it. For that ſome ſéeke to auoyde it, in poſting ouer this whole writing to bée againſt <hi>Iohn</hi> the B. of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> as though <hi>Gregorie</hi> had miſliked this name of vniuerſal Biſhop in him ſo ambitiouſly &amp; gréedily ſéeking for it, &amp; not if it had ben giuen to his own Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> this is but a méere ſhift. For thus he ſayth in <hi>32</hi> Epiſtle, <hi>Nullus Romanorum E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcoporum hoc ſingularitatis nome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſibi aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. Epi. <hi>32</hi>
               </note> None of the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> euer rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued this name of ſingularitie. And againe <hi>Nullus predeceſſoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hoc tam profano vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabulo vti conſenſit,</hi> None of my Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours euer conſented to vſe this vngodlye name, <hi>Nos hunc oblatum honorem nol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mus
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:26495:36"/> ſuſcipere,</hi> We will not take this honour of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered vnto vs, and in very déede no more he would, for in his ſeueth Booke hee findeth fault with <hi>Eulogius</hi> the Patriarch of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantinople,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 7.30.</note> for terming him in the preface of his Epiſtle the vniuerſall Pope, and for ſaying (as you commanded) requiring him to doe ſo no more, and not to vſe any ſuche tearmes. So that he diſaloweth that name and authoritie to be giuen to himſelfe as well as to the Biſhop of <hi>Constantinople.</hi> This that <hi>Gregorie</hi> did, to diſallow the authoritie of Vniuerſall Biſhop in anye, was not onely done by him, but alſo by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers other learned and godly Biſhops, yea and by Councels. Firſt, that is cleare which <hi>Cyprian</hi> that godlye man and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tir of God writeth in his Oration he made in the Councell of <hi>Carthage</hi> concerning this poynt, it remaineth, ſaith <hi>Cyprian,</hi> that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerye one ſpeake of this thing what hée thinketh. For there is none of vs that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth himſelfe Biſhop of Biſhops, or that doth by tyrannicall feare driue his Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes to obey of neceſſitie, ſeing euerye Biſhop at his pleaſure, hath frée libertye and power of his owne will, as if he could not be iudged of another, neyther yet him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:26495:36"/> iudge any other, let vs all waite for the iudgement of our ſauiour Chriſt, who only and alone hath power to make vs go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours of his Church, and iudge of oure doing. Thus <hi>Cyprian</hi> denieth to anye to chalenge to himſelfe to be Biſhop of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, that is to bee vniuerſall Biſhop, to haue power and authoritie ouer the reſt, to compell them to obay, and to iudge of them he giueth frée libertie to all Biſhops alike in that, and giueth that preheminence to Chriſt alone, whoſe of right it is.<note place="margin">Pela. Ep. <hi>99</hi>
               </note> That which <hi>Pelagius</hi> alſo writeth, who was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Gregorie</hi> is playne. Let none of the Patriarkes, ſayth he, at any time vſe this name of vniuerſalitie, becauſe if one Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarke be called vniuerſall, the name of Patriarch is thereby taken awaye from the other, But let this be farre from the Faithfull. The wordes of <hi>pelagius</hi> and <hi>Gregorie</hi> be ſo plaine, that <hi>Edmundus Rufus</hi> writing agaynſte <hi>Molinaeus</hi> the Lawyer, cannot tell how to auoyde them, he is driuen to interprete this worde <hi>vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſalis ſingularis,</hi> the vniuerſall Biſhop, that is the ſinguler and only Biſhop. But God wot, this poore ſhift will not ſerue the turne, for the gréeke worde <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:26495:37"/> the Biſhop of the whole habitable worlde quite ouerthroweth that, for it cannot bee expounded the onelye Biſhop. The diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liking of this preheminence and power which the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> nowe challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to himſelfe, was not only gaynſayde by their Biſhops priuate opinions, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by Councels.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onc. Carth. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> For in the Councell of <hi>Carthage</hi> it was decréede, that the Biſhop of the firſte Sea bee not called the chéefe of Prieſtes, or the high Prieſt or by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like name, but onelye the Biſhop of the firſt Sea, by whiche name hee was tearmed, not for any principalitie or po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, he had aboue the other Patriarkes but becauſe the Romane Empire was the chéefe, therefore the Biſhop of that ſea was tearmed by that name, and tooke the place in Councels at that tyme, and yet had no further authoritie, then the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarche of <hi>Conſtantinople, Alexandria,</hi> or <hi>Antioche,</hi> I omitte the Councell of <hi>Hippo Rhegius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Conc. Hippo cap. <hi>27.</hi> Conc. Africa. cap. <hi>92.</hi>
               </note> and of <hi>Africa,</hi> by which it appeareth too manifeſtlye, what was the iudgemente of the Churche at thoſe tymes, concerning the geuing any prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall power or prerogatiue to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome aboue all others. It is
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:26495:37"/> playne by the Hiſtorye of tymes, that they neuer heald any ſuche Article, that it was of the neceſſitie of ſaluation, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue the whole Churche of GOD muſt bée vnder one heade, one generall, of whome they muſt depende, they would neuer yéelde or conſent to any ſuche de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crée or conſtitution. It is well knowne how that <hi>Gregory</hi> the firſt Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> of that name called <hi>Iohn</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> the forerunner of Anti-Chriſt, for ambitiouſlye deſyring to be ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme heade,<note place="margin">Greg. lib. <hi>2</hi> Cap. <hi>194.</hi>
               </note> and to bee called the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall Biſhop of the World that was ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitable. Halfe a ſcore yeare after, or little more, <hi>Boniface</hi> the third of that name, obtayned through the helpe of <hi>Phocas</hi> the Emperoure, whome hée had helped vnto the Empire, by killing <hi>Mauritius</hi> the former Emperour, his wife, his brother, and his ſonne, with many other, to bee na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med or ordeined Pope, or <hi>ſummus Pontifex,</hi> the high Biſhop, which authoritie encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed afterward more &amp; more, vntill it came to the higheſt pride. So that apparant it is, that the Churches of God, for the ſpace of foure hundred yeares, and more after the death of our Sauiour Chriſt, neuer
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:26495:38"/> taught, or receiued any ſuch doctrine, either out of this place of <hi>Mathew,</hi> or anye other that Chriſt hath left after his aſcenſion an head of his vniuerſal church here in earth, or appointed an vniuerſall Paſtor of the whole congregation vnder him. Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall ambition begate this office firſt, and mans conſtitutions and Traditions hath only confirmed the ſame. This I truſt, I haue ſufficiently declared according as I promiſed, both by the interpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the antient and learned Fathers of this place of <hi>Mathew,</hi> and by their generall opinion, concerning the appointing of an Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall Biſhop ouer Gods Churche, as alſo by the practiſe of that age in that behalfe. Wherein I am the more ſparing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it hath bene at large declared of others in this age, that there is no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitye in this worde <hi>Petra,</hi> in this place to make Peter the Foundation of the Congregation of Chriſte, and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentlye his Succeſſoure, but lette vs graunte thus muche, that Peter was made that Rocke, that hée were the chéefe, and Prince of the Apoſtles how doth it followe therefore, that the Biſhop of Rome is the Foundation and the chéefe of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:26495:38"/> all Biſhops. It wil be ſaide that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> is <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſour, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whatſoeuer prerogatiue was giuen vnto <hi>Peter,</hi> was alſo giuen to him. Firſt beſides this conſequent followeth not, not to driue them to prooue that euer <hi>Peter</hi> was at <hi>Rome,</hi> which they are not able by any ſound proofe out of the Scripture, being great preſumptions to the contrary, neither yet by any agreement of Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall writers, not agréeing of the tyme of his comming or abode there: I woulde gladly knowe why and wherein the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> is rather accounted <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſour, then any other Biſhop. If it be becauſe <hi>Peter</hi> was at <hi>Rome,</hi> ſo was he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and at <hi>Antioche</hi> as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in the actes of the Apoſtles, why ſhould not then the Biſhops of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> and <hi>Antioche</hi> be accounted <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours, as well as the Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi> If it be becauſe <hi>Peter</hi> ſuffred there, ſo did <hi>Paul</hi> alſo, and ſurely that is but a meane reaſon to make <hi>Rome</hi> the Sea of <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſion, becauſe that citie put him to death. But wherein are the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> his ſucceſſours, whether in his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtleſhip, or in his Biſhoprike, not in the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:26495:39"/> former, for then muſt they immediatly be called to that office of God. Secondly, their duetie muſt be to preache to all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: for both theſe properties be required to make an Apoſtle as may appeare <hi>Gal. 1. Matth. 28.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. <hi>Matth.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8.</note> But neither of theſe are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gréeable to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> being neither immediatly called of God, neither executing the office of an Apoſtle in going about to preache to all nations, he cannot be his ſucceſſour in his Biſhopricke, for neither doeth hee take vppon him the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of a Biſhop to be tyed to a certaine charge, and beſides, how can he be ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour to <hi>Peter</hi> in that which <hi>Peter</hi> was not, he was by office an Apoſtle, not a Biſhop. And further, if we will beléeue auncient writers,<note place="margin">Irenaeus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Valent.</note> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> was neuer Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> for <hi>Irenaeus</hi> and <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſay, that <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> founded the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and that <hi>Linus</hi> by them was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed the firſt Biſhop. Then ſucceded him <hi>Anacletus,</hi> and thirdly <hi>Clemens.</hi> And <hi>Tertullian</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tert. lib. <hi>10.</hi> de preſ. heret.</note> nameth <hi>Clemens</hi> the firſt Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> appointed by <hi>Peter,</hi> as <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licarpus</hi> was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Smirna</hi> appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Iohn.</hi> Thus although <hi>Tertullian</hi> agreeth not with <hi>Irenaeus</hi> and <hi>Euſebius</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:26495:39"/> in appointing the firſt Biſhop, yet it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident, that neither of them accounted of <hi>Peter</hi> as of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> but as of an Apoſtle, who taught there as <hi>Paul</hi> did alſo. So that the Pope cannot be <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> ſucceſſour in his Biſhopricke, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee was neuer Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi> If hee ſaye, hee is his ſucceſſour in his doctrine, if he were able to iuſtifie that it woulde beare ſome colour. But if the quite contrarie be prooued, then is that allegation nothinge, and beſides that ought to be common to all Biſhops, and therefore by that he can challenge no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue.</p>
            <p>I might declare at large howe farre he is from ſuccéeding <hi>Peter</hi> in many reſpects, but that were too large a fielde to enter in, but euen as all thoſe be not the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Abraham,</hi> which come of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> concerning the fleſh, but thoſe that doe the workes of <hi>Abraham,</hi> euen ſo thoſe are not to be eſtéemed the ſucceſſours of <hi>Peter,</hi> or any of the Apoſtles, which followe them in place or in name, but thoſe which followe them in their faith and doctrine, which thing if they can ſhewe they doe, we will in parte graunt
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:26495:40"/> them to be ſucceſſours to the Apoſtles. I will not ſtande longer vppon this point, I truſt that which I haue ſayd ſhalbe ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, for the confirmation of the ſecond part part I tooke in hande to prooue. Nowe I will haſten vnto the third.</p>
            <p>There remaineth then the third parte to diſcuſſe, which was, what the power &amp; commiſſion is that was giuen to <hi>Peter</hi> in this place, when it is ſaide to him: <hi>To thee wil I giue the keyes of the kingdom of Heauen, whatſoeuer thou ſhalt binde on earth, ſhalbe bounde in Heauen, &amp;c.</hi> which wordes being ſpoken vnto <hi>Peter</hi> &amp; giuing him by expreſſe wordes the keyes of the kingdome of Heauen, and the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of binding and looſing, thereby they haue inferred ſome ſpeciall authoritie and prerogatiue to haue bene giuen to <hi>Peter</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all other by our Sauiour Chriſt in this place. Wherefore concerning the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation and ſenſe of theſe wordes ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there is no agréement betwéene vs &amp; the church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in that they ſaye, that hereby <hi>Peter</hi> was endewed with ſpeciall commiſſion aboue all other the Apoſtles, &amp; we contrariwiſe doe affirme that, that which was ſpoken vnto him was ſpoken
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:26495:40"/> to all the reſt alike. For the better exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of this, it ſhalbe neceſſarie for vs to conſider theſe two pointes: Firſt, vnto whome theſe wordes were ſpoken, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnto <hi>Peter</hi> alone, or principally, as the Papiſtes woulde haue it, or vnto all in generall. Secondly, what is that power and authoritie which was giuen vnto <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> for in neither of theſe points do wee agree with them. For the firſt, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though theſe wordes were directed to <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> alone, yet that thereby our Sauiour Chriſt meant not to giue him any ſpeciall priuilege or prerogatiue aboue his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, but to endew them al with the like authoritie, firſt, both the wordes and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of the place, and the doctrine of the ſcriptures in other places doth declare it: and ſecondly the iudgement and opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the auncient &amp; learned fathers, doth approue the ſame. That the whole courſe and circumſtance of the place doeth euict this promiſe &amp; gift of our Sauiour Chriſt, to appertaine to them all, it may be appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant by this. Firſt, that the queſtion of our Sauiour Chriſt is propounded to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all. Whome do ye ſay that I am, and therefore he requireth not the opinion of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:26495:41"/> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> alone, but of them all, that their knowledge and opinion of him, may better agree, and be more conſtant, truer, &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecter than the opinion of the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which before they had declared vnto him. And the aunſwere alſo <hi>Peter</hi> made, was not in his owne perſon alone, but for them all. So ſayeth <hi>Auſtine</hi> as was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged of mee before: The Lorde aſking and ſaying (ſaith he) <hi>Whome do ye ſaye that I the ſonne of man am? Peter</hi> aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth: <hi>Thou art the ſonne of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God,</hi> one gaue aunſwere for many. The concluſion of the dialogue appertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth alſo vnto all: for in the ende Chriſt forbad not onely <hi>Peter</hi> to tell any bodie, that he was Ieſus that Chriſt, but he char<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged them all to tell that to no man. So that the beginning of the dialogue, the middeſt, and the ending, appertaining to all, why then ſhoulde any ſpeciall thing be attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to any one aboue others by theſe wordes. Beſides that which is ſpoken here alone to <hi>Peter</hi> in the ſingular num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in the <hi>18.</hi> Chapter, is ſpoken to all in the plurall number. <hi>Verily I ſaie vnto you, whatſoeuer ye binde in earth, ſhall be bound in Heauen, and whatſoeuer ye
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:26495:41"/> looſe in earth, ſhalbe looſed in Heauen.</hi> Here equall authoritie is giuen to all in the ſame wordes. But let vs obſerue fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that Chriſt ſaith here, <hi>Dabo, <hi>I will giue thee the keyes of the kingdome of Heauen,</hi>
               </hi> and ſo forth. Here the keyes are promiſed but not giuen. If then Chriſt when he perfourmed this promiſe, gaue not any ſpecial power to <hi>Peter,</hi> but endued them all with the like, ſhall we imagine here any ſpecial thing giuen him to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before others, in the <hi>20.</hi> of <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 20.</note> where Chriſt perfourmed this after his reſurrection, he committed this power and authoritie he promiſed here vnto al equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in theſe wordes: <hi>Peace be vnto you, as my father ſent me, euen ſo ſende I you,</hi> &amp; when he had ſaid that, he breathed vpon them, &amp; they receiued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Ghoſt, adding <hi>Whoſe ſoeuer ſinnes ye remit, they are remitted vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; whoſe ſoeuer ſinnes ye retain, they are retained.</hi> Here we ſée he giueth his peace vnto them al: he breatheth on them all: they all receiue the holy ghoſt alike: they are al endewed with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of forgiuing &amp; reteining ſins. Where is then <hi>Peters</hi> prerogatiue? eſpecially now when it ſhould ſpecially haue bin ſpecified.
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:26495:42"/> But what if any principall authoritie and power had béene giuen to <hi>Peter</hi> by Chriſt here, what doth that belong to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome:</hi> where is <hi>Peters</hi> will and teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by which he hath bequeathed his keyes, rather vnto him than vnto the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> or <hi>Antioche,</hi> by what Scripture can they proue that Chriſt hath made them rather <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſours in this authoritie and commiſſion then other Biſhops. If the keyes were promiſed, &amp; giuen to <hi>Peter</hi> alone, and to none of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Apoſtles, howe dare they giue them vnto the Biſhops of <hi>Rome.</hi> There is not one worde in the Scripture of their ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion by inheritance. Seing then that neither the courſe of the dialogue, nor yet the authoritie and function is other, that is here giuen, then was giuen to all the Apoſtles of Chriſt, himſelfe afterwarde in like manner, and that although ſome more ſpeciall and excellent office was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to <hi>Peter,</hi> then to any other Apoſtle, yet that the B. of <hi>Rome</hi> cannot claim that more than any other Biſhop, it maketh nothing for the eſtabliſhing of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſupreme power ouer the vniuerſall Church of God which the Pope arrogateth vnto himſelf.
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:26495:42"/> But let vs ſée what the auncient &amp; learned fathers thinke on this point. That which <hi>Origen</hi> writeth is moſt plaine againſt them which think any ſpeciall thing was giuen to <hi>Peter. <hi>An ſoli Petro dantur claues regni coelorum &amp;c.</hi> Doeſt thou thinke that the keyes of the kingdom were only giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to Peter and to no other, neither any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould receiue them?</hi> If theſe words were not common to all men as they are <hi>(I will giue thee the keyes of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen)</hi> how can al theſe ſayings &amp; things which are applyed to <hi>Peter</hi> before be common to all men. For Chriſt thus ſpake in common to them all, <hi>Whome do ye ſaye that I am?</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> anſwered in the name of all. Doeth he not vtter the ſame in plainer wordes in the <hi>20.</hi> of <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaying to all the Apoſtles,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 20.</note> and breathing vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them: <hi>receiue the holie Ghoſt, whoſe ſinnes ye forgiue, &amp;c.</hi> They were all of like authoritie with <hi>Peter.</hi> Thus much <hi>Origen,</hi> then which wordes, what can be more plaine. <hi>Cyprian</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cyp. de ſimp. praelat.</note> alſo in his booke <hi>de ſimplicitate Prelatorum</hi> againſt the <hi>Nouati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> confirmeth this. The Lord (ſayth he) ſaith vnto <hi>Peter, thou art Peter.</hi> The Lord after his reſurrection gaue vnto his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:26495:43"/> like power, yet to declare the vnitie, he diſpoſed the originall of vnitie begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth at one. The reſt of the Apoſtles were euen the ſame that <hi>Peter</hi> was, endewed with like fellowſhip both of honour and power, but the beginning procéedeth of v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie to declare one Church. <hi>Baſil</hi>
               <note place="margin">Baſil. <hi>23.</hi> cap. de vita ſolit.</note> alſo ſayeth: <hi>Chriſtus Petrum poſt ſe ſuae Eccleſiae pastorem conſtituit &amp;c.</hi> Chriſt appointed <hi>Peter</hi> to be Paſtor of his Church after, and ſo conſequently giueth the ſame po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and authoritie to all Paſtours and doctours, a token whereof is this that all Paſtours, doe equally binde and loſe as they liſt, as well as he. <hi>Auguſtine, <hi>de Agone Chriſtiano Cap.</hi> 32. <hi>Cum Petro dicitur paſce oues meas, omnibus dicitur.</hi>
               </hi> When it is ſayde to <hi>Peter</hi> féede my ſhéepe,<note place="margin">Auſt. de A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon. Chriſt. cap. <hi>31.</hi> &amp; cap. <hi>32.</hi>
               </note> it is ſaide to all. And in the <hi>31.</hi> Chapter: Wretched men while in <hi>Peter</hi> they vnderſtande not Chriſt which is the rocke, and while they wil not beléeue that the keyes of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heauen, are giuen vnto the Church (not vnto <hi>Peter</hi> alone) they haue loſt the keyes out of their handes, and in another place hee ſayeth, the Churche which is founded in Chriſt,<note place="margin">Aug. tract. <hi>124.</hi> ſaper</note> hath taken the keyes of him, ſo that not <hi>Peter</hi> onely,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:26495:43"/> but the whole Church receiued the keyes of him. <hi>Beda</hi>
               <note place="margin">Beda.</note> ſayeth, the power of byn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and looſing, although it ſeeme to be giuen onely vnto <hi>Peter,</hi> without doubt this is to bee knowen, that it is giuen al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo vnto the other Apoſtles. <hi>Haymo,</hi> one of their owne doctors well weighing the text affirmeth contrarie vnto them. Wee muſt not thinke, ſayeth hee, that vnto bleſſed <hi>Peter</hi> alone this power was giuen. but as hee for all aunſwered, <hi>Thou art Chriſt the ſonne of the liuing God,</hi> ſo in the perſon of one, all heard, <hi>whatſoeuer thou ſhalt binde in earth, &amp;c. Cyrill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cyr. in Ioan. li. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> Chriſt gaue full power vnto the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and vnto others that ſucceeded them in the Churches. To conclude then, if by the teſtimonyes of the auncient and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned fathers, Chriſt gaue full and like po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to all his Apoſtles. If the reſt of the Apoſtles were the ſame that <hi>Peter</hi> was, endewed all with like honour and power. If Chriſtes wordes were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all the reſt. If all Paſtours doe equally binde and looſe as well as <hi>Peter,</hi> then is there no ſpeciall priuilege giuen vnto <hi>Peter</hi> aboue others by this place. Wherefore I truſt this firſt poynt is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:26495:44"/> by the circumſtance of the place and opinion of ancient writers that there is no ſpeciall prerogatiue or function giuen vnto <hi>Peter,</hi> that was not committed to all, &amp; that whatſoeuer was ſpoken by Chriſt here vnto <hi>Peter</hi> did not belong here vnto him only, but to them al in common. Now ſecondly haue wee to conſider what was that power &amp; authoritie that was giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Peter</hi> here, that was to haue the keyes of the kingdom of heauen, the authoritie of binding &amp; looſing, but herein haue wee to weigh what is meant &amp; contained in theſe words &amp; how farre they ought to ſtretch. For the B. of <hi>Rome</hi> claimeth by right of ſucceſſion &amp; inheritance whatſoeuer power &amp; iuriſdiction was giuen vnto <hi>Peter,</hi> &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore by the vertue of theſe wordes, &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of Chriſt, claimeth al power &amp; autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, whatſoeuer may be contained &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in theſe ſpeaches. Hereof hath he challenged to himſelfe to be aboue kings &amp; Princes, to haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> authoritie of conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting &amp; depoſing them, to be aboue all gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral councels to haue fulnes of power to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound the ſcriptures, to whoſe determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the Church of God muſt neceſſarily ſtand, to haue authoritie to diſpenſe with
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:26495:44"/> Gods worde, to make that lawfull which before was vnlawfull, to haue abſolute, &amp; frée power to decree whatſoeuer he liketh of, and that of the church is to be obſerued as an heauenly Oracle, that he hath power to giue heauen, to throwe downe into hell whome he will, that he hath power to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoyle mens ſinnes, and to deliuer them both <hi>a pena &amp; culpa,</hi> both from the fault &amp; penaltie, and to reteine and kéepe them at his pleaſure, that he may binde and looſe aboue all other Biſhops: for he may looſe whome other Biſhops binde: he may bind whome other Biſhops looſe: but whome he bindeth or looſeth can no man aſſoyle or binde, but onely he himſelfe: for Bulles, pardons, indulgencies, anathematizations and all the reſt of ſuch triſhtraſh, hath béen founded vpon this power and prerogatiue he challengeth vnto him ſelf by this place, the refutation of which particuler pointes being too ample a matter to be handled at this time, and beſides hauing ſufficiently both in this ſeconde part, and alſo in the thirde, declared and proued that no prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue is giuen vnto <hi>Peter</hi> aboue others by this place, that his miniſterie was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dewed with no greater power and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:26495:45"/> then the miniſterie of the reſt of the Apoſtles, it ſhalbee needeleſſe to deale with them at this preſent, onely that is needefull to ſhewe what is meant by the keyes of the kingdome of heauen, and the authoritie of bynding and looſing. By the keyes is meant nothing elſe here but the preaching of the Goſpell, and herein wee agree with <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cryſostom.</note> that ſayeth, they are the knowledge of the Scriptures, with <hi>Tertullian</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertullian.</note> which tearmeth them to bee the interpretation of the lawe, and with <hi>Euſebius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſebius.</note> that they are the worde of GOD. and verie well may the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the worde bee expreſſed by the Metaphore of a keye. For as by it wee are let into the houſe, ſo by the preaching of the worde, are wee brought into the Church and houſholde of GOD, and haue acceſſe to his kingdome. For Chriſt being the dore, as <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> teſtifieth, by whome wee muſt enter, if wee will be ſaued, and the ladder, by which wee muſt aſcende vp into heauen, as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by <hi>Iacobs</hi> dreame, and the preaching of the Goſpell, opening and manifeſting vnto vs Chriſt, as <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſeth, that vnto him the leaſt of al Saints was giuen
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:26495:45"/> this grace, that hee ſhoulde preach among the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> the vnſearchable riches of Chriſt, and being the meanes, whereby wee are reconciled vnto Chriſt, <hi>Paul</hi> tearming his miniſterie therefore the miniſterie of reconciliation, the publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing and preachinge of Chriſt and his Goſpell, may well therefore be tearmed a keye. This Metaphore is vſed of our Sauiour Chriſt in the ſame ſenſe. Woe be to you interpreters of the lawe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 12.52.</note> for you haue taken away the keye of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. Ye entred not in your ſelues, and them that came yee forbad, in which wordes our Sauiour Chriſt termeth the true interpretation of the lawe and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the Goſpel, the key of knowledge. For it was that the Scribes &amp; Phariſes did ſuppreſſe &amp; adulterate. It is apparant enough, that the worde of God, according to the ſundry effectes and properties ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hath ſundrie names. So for that it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth and multiplyeth, it is called ſéede, for that it cutteth the heart, and deuydeth the fleſhe from the Spirite, it is called a Sworde. For that it taketh vs, and encloſeth vs, and bringeth vs togither, it is called a nett. For that it waſheth
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:26495:46"/> vs cleane it is called water. For that it enflameth vs, it is called fire. For that it féedeth vs it is called bread: euen ſo for that it openeth &amp; giueth vs an entrance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the houſe, it is called a keye. This houſe is the kingdome of heauen: Chriſt is the dore: the worde of God is the keye, and Preachers the keye bearers. So ſayeth <hi>Chryſoſtom:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſ. opere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nperfect. cap. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> The keye bearers be the Prieſtes, to whome is committed the tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the worde, and of the expounding of the Scriptures: So then, that by the Metaphore of the keye, the Euangeliſt ſhould declare that Chriſt committed vnto his Apoſtles, the preaching of his worde, by which his Church ſhould be gathered togither, and built vppon Chriſt the rocke, is no ſtrange ſpeach, but verie fit and ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant, to declare that vnto vs, and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by alſo he ſheweth that he hath committed vnto them a great office and weightie fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and that he putteth them in chiefe place and authoritie. For he hath the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt authoritie in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe or citie to whome the keyes are committed, and who hath authoritie to let out and let in by them. To this end God vſeth this Metaphore in the Prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 22.22.</note> when he promiſeth to
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:26495:46"/> 
               <hi>Eliachim</hi> the chéefe power and authoritie in the King <hi>Ezechias</hi> houſe, ſaying: with my garments I will cloath him, with my girdle I will ſtrengthen him, and the keye of the houſe of <hi>Dauid</hi> will I lay vppon his ſhoulder, ſo he ſhall open, and no man ſhall ſhut. Hereby haue we to learne, that as thoſe to whome this charge is committed to beare the keyes of the Kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, ought to haue a great care of the well ordering of them, ſo we muſt alſo with no leſſe carefulneſſe and reuerence, embrace and receyue them. The vſe of theſe keyes is in more perticular manner declared by our Sauiour Chriſt, when as he ſaith that whatſoeuer he bindeth on earth ſhall bée bound in heauen, &amp;c. by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power of binding and loſing is meant that which is expreſſed by Saint Iohn. Whoſe ſinnes yee forgiue, they are forgiuen him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 20.</note> and whoſe ſinnes ye retayne, they are retayned, for when our ſinnes are forgiuen, we are loſed from them, &amp; when they are not forgiuen, wée remayne bound in them, theſe things are brought to paſſe in vs by the miniſterie of his word, and by the vertue and power thereof. So ſayth <hi>Ierome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hieron. Eſai. lib. <hi>6</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> whatſoeuer yée looſe in earth, ſhall be loſed in Heauen, the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:26495:47"/> Apoſtles loſe them by the worde of God, and teſtimonies of the ſcriptures, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations vnto vertue. And <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> Sinnes be forgiuen by the worde of God, the expounder thereof is the Leuite and Prieſt.<note place="margin">Ambr. de Cain &amp; A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel. cap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> The Prophet <hi>Eſai</hi> prophecying the ſending of Chriſt, ſayth that the Lorde had annointed him that he ſhoulde preache the Goſpell to the poore, that he ſhoulde heale the broken hearted and preach deliuerance to the Captiue, recouering of ſighte to the blind, and ſetting at libertie them that are looſed: ſo that to binde and looſe, to forgiue and retaine ſinnes, is a propertie and effect of the worde of God preached. For that publiſheth vnto vs remiſſion of ſinnes, worketh in vs mortification, deliuereth vs from the power of Sathan, and reſtoreth vnto vs the libertie and fréedome of the children of God, which thinges bée brought to paſſe, not by the bare publiſhing and hearing of the worde, but when as by faith we lay hold vpon the ſwéete promiſes, and greate benefites which bée offered vs in Chriſt, which be deliuered vnto vs by his miniſters, as by his Legates, for remiſſion of ſinnes is in the Prieſt, as in the meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, in the worde of God as in the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:26495:47"/> and in the penitent, as in the recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. So that the offering hereof is in the miniſter, but the effect and force thereof in the ſinner. But for as muche as they offer the merites of Chriſt, and full pardon to ſuch as haue lowly and contrite harts, and doe vnfainedly repent themſelues, pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing vnto the ſame a ſure and vndoubted forgiueneſſe of their ſinnes, and hope of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting life, therefore they are ſayde to binde and loſe, to reteine and forgiue ſins, not becauſe God hath endued his mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters with this abſolute power to forgiue and reteine them at their pleaſure, as our popiſhe Prieſts woulde beare vs in hand, for that hee hath reſerued vnto him alone, and it only belongeth vnto him. Euen the verye malicious Scribes and Phariſeis knew this, for when as Chriſte had ſayde vnto the man ſick of the Palſey, ſonne thy ſinnes are forgiuen, they not acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging him to be God, ſayd among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Marc.</hi> 2.5.</note> this man blaſphemeth, who can forgiue ſinnes but God only. And God by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Eſai</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſai.</note> challengeth this vnto himſelfe, I euen I am he that putteth away thine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, euen as to create, to alter &amp; change the heart, to deſtroy body and ſoule belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:26495:48"/> only vnto God, and ſo alſo to forgiue and reteine ſinnes. The antient Fathers haue iudged that the Prieſt ought to haue no right to challenge any authoritie to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue ſinnes. <hi>Ambroſe</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambr. li. <hi>9.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>76.</hi>
               </note> ſayth, it is not the Embaſſadour, it is not the Meſſenger, but the Lord himſelfe hath ſaued his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. He remaineth one, for this cannot bée common to any man with Chriſte to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue ſinnes, that is only the office of Chriſt who hath borne the ſinnes of the worlde. And <hi>Auſtine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> God gaue the miniſterie of forgiuing of ſinnes to his ſeruauntes, but the power thereof he retained to himſelfe.<note place="margin">Auguſt. de ſcalis Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſi.</note> So in another place, the office of baptizing God hath graunted vnto many: the power and authoritie of forgiuing ſinnes, he hath reſerued to himſelfe alone. Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> expounding this place very well declareth what power and commiſſion is giuen to Gods miniſters in this behalfe.<note place="margin">Hierony.</note> We reade in ſcriptures that the Leapers are bidden to ſhew themſelues vnto the Prieſt, that if they be Leapers, they ſhould be ſo made of the Prieſt, not that the Prieſt doe make the leaprous or vncleane, but that they haue knowledge of the leaprous and clean perſon, that they are able to iudge who is
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:26495:48"/> cleane or vncleane, euen therefore as the Prieſt maketh the cleane or vncleane, ſo doth the Biſhop here bind and loſe, hereby we ſée that <hi>Ierome</hi> thought Miniſters had no further power, then to declare them to be loſe or bound, euen as the Prieſts in the time of the law, had no power but to iudge and pronounce the man eyther cleane or vnclean, but not to clenſe them, or to make them vncleane. So ſayth <hi>Bonauentura,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bonauentura.</note> they did clenſe becauſe they ſhewed the cleane. <hi>Peter Lumbard,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pet. Lumb.</note> one of their owne Doctors, ſayth, hauing well weighed this matter. Chriſt gaue to prieſts authority to binde or loſe, that is to declare to men they bee bounde or loſe: What therefore the authoritie of binding and looſing, the forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and reteining of ſinnes is, that is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the miniſters of God, it is apparant not to haue giuen ful power to abſolue and binde of themſelues at their will, but to publiſh that pardon that God in Chriſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth vs, which if we take hold on by faith then we are aſſoiled, if we contemne it our ſinnes are reteined to oure condemnation, and becauſe he hath committed the publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of forgiueneſſe of ſinnes vnto his miniſters, therefore his miniſters are ſaid
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:26495:49"/> to forgiue and reteine, not becauſe the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer thereof reſteth in themſelues, as our popiſh prieſts would chalenge: For there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore haue they made the Prieſt to holde a conſiſtory, and to be a iudge ouer the ſinnes of the people, and to driue them to make particular confeſſion of their ſecrete ſinnes vnto the Prieſt, that they may abſolue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and enioyne them a penaunce anſwerable to their offence. Howſoeuer they go about to cloke and colour the matter, in very déed they take vpon them that which is proper to God to iudge of the weight &amp; gréeuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinnes to appoint and alot to euery one a iuſt ſatiſfaction, to chaunge eternall paynes into temporall, to haue the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the merites of Chriſt, euen as the Executors haue the diſpoſing of dead mens goods, as though Chriſt were not, or knew not after his death, how to beſtow them, to geue Heauen and throwe downe to Hell, whome they will, to rehearſe the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar blaſphemies and impieties, whiche by the keyes of heauen, and authoritie of bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and looſing they claime, they haue run into, although it were profitable, to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the abhominations of that Church, yet leaſt I ſhould grow infinite, it ſhalbe ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciente
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:26495:49"/> to haue but lightlye touched theſe thinges. Thus I truſt I haue ſufficientlye declared, firſt that God reuealeth the know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge of all heauenly thinges, Secondlye that not <hi>Peter,</hi> but Chriſte is the Rocke whereon God doth build his Church, and laſt of all that the keyes of the kingdome of heauen, and the authoritie of binding and looſing conſiſteth in the preaching of his word. God of his mercye graunt vnto vs, the reuealing of his Chriſt, and to be builte vpon him the true rocke, and the opening of the kingdome of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by the preaching of his worde, that wee maye obtayne that bleſſedneſſe, which Chriſte hath prepared for them that truly acknowledge and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe him, To whome with the Father and the holy Ghoſt be al honour and glory, and power, now and for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
